[
  {
    "questionNum": 87001,
    "questionText": " The Treaty of Mysore was signed between Tipu and the British in?",
    "answerText": 1784
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87002,
    "questionText": " The Treaty of Purandhar was signed between the English and the Peshwa in?",
    "answerText": 1776
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87003,
    "questionText": " The tribal leader who was came to be known as ‘Bhagawan’?",
    "answerText": " Birsa Munda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87004,
    "questionText": " Bethune School in Calcutta, set up in 1849, founded by?",
    "answerText": " John Elliot Drinkwater Bethune (established as a girls' school in 1849; and as a college in 1879)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87005,
    "questionText": " Between the period 1858-1947 , how many Governors General ruled over India?",
    "answerText": " Twenty"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87006,
    "questionText": " Bhagat Singh was hanged in?",
    "answerText": 1931
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87007,
    "questionText": " Bihar Vidyapeeth was founded by?",
    "answerText": " Rajendra Prasad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87008,
    "questionText": " Birla Mandir, where Gandhiji was assassinated, is in?",
    "answerText": " New Delhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87009,
    "questionText": " The date in which Gandhiji violated salt law in Dandi beach?",
    "answerText": " 1930 April 6"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87010,
    "questionText": " The Dev Samaj founded in 1887 had its headquarters at?",
    "answerText": " Lahore"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87011,
    "questionText": " Name the person who resigned his position as Viceroy of India in August 1905 because of a difference of opinion with Lord Kitchener, the British military Commander-in-Chief in India?",
    "answerText": " Lord Curzon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87012,
    "questionText": " Name the Peshwa whose reign was dominated by the political intrigues of Nana Fadnavis?",
    "answerText": " Madhav Rao II"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87013,
    "questionText": " Name the residence of Mahathma Gandhi in Ahmedabad from where he began his salt Satyagraha in 1930?",
    "answerText": " Hriday Kunj"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87014,
    "questionText": " Name the revolutionary leader who turned into an ascetic in the later years of his life?",
    "answerText": " Aurobindo Ghosh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87015,
    "questionText": " Name the revolutionary who was shot dead in an encounter with police at a public park in Allahabad?",
    "answerText": " Chandrasekhar Azad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87016,
    "questionText": " Name the ruler who was deposed in 1875 on charges of ‘gross misrule’?",
    "answerText": " Malhar Rao Gaikwad of Baroda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87017,
    "questionText": " Name the Viceroy who delegated W.W.Hunter to prepare the ‘Imperial Gazetteer of India’?",
    "answerText": " Mayo"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87018,
    "questionText": " The disciple of Gandhiji who started Bhoodan Movement?",
    "answerText": " Vinoba Bhave"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87019,
    "questionText": " The disciples who were with Gandhiji when he passed away?",
    "answerText": " Manu and Aabha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87020,
    "questionText": " The Dual system of Government in Bengal was a brain child of?",
    "answerText": " Robert Clive"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87021,
    "questionText": " In 1922 Gandhiji was sentenced for —— years imprisonment?",
    "answerText": 6
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87022,
    "questionText": " Name the nationalist leader whose birth day is August 15?",
    "answerText": " Aurobindo Ghosh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87023,
    "questionText": " Name the Viceroy who was called the “Aurangazeb of British India’?",
    "answerText": " Curzon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87024,
    "questionText": " Name the Viceroy who was the supreme commander of the Allied Forces in South East Asia during the Second World War?",
    "answerText": " Mountbatten"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87025,
    "questionText": " National Herald was started by?",
    "answerText": " Jawaharlal Nehru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87026,
    "questionText": " Nehru Report was prepared by Motilal Nehru was reaction to the?",
    "answerText": " Simon Commission"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87027,
    "questionText": " Baba Ram Chandra Das was a leader of?",
    "answerText": " Peasants"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87028,
    "questionText": " Bahadur Shah Zafar who was deported by the British after the 1857 mutiny,died in the Rangoon jail in?",
    "answerText": 1862
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87029,
    "questionText": " Bal Gangadhar Tilak published ‘Mahratha’ in .....language?",
    "answerText": " English"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87030,
    "questionText": " Before becoming the Governor General in India who had served in America and commanded the British Generals in the American Civil war?",
    "answerText": " Cornwallis"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87031,
    "questionText": " Before independence who served as the president of Indian National Congress for the longest continous period?",
    "answerText": " Maulana Abul Kalam Azad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87032,
    "questionText": " ‘Bombay Chronicle’ was started by?",
    "answerText": " Pheroz Shah Mehta"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87033,
    "questionText": " All India Khilafat Committee observed Khilafat day on _____, 1919?",
    "answerText": " October 17"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87034,
    "questionText": " The Viceroy who used to write poems with the pen name ‘Owen Meredith’?",
    "answerText": " Lytton"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87035,
    "questionText": " Who was the founder of Amritsar?",
    "answerText": " Guru Ram Das"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87036,
    "questionText": " What was the court language of Mughals?",
    "answerText": " Persian"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87037,
    "questionText": " Who was the head of the British Government in India when the congress for the first time passed its famous resolution for complete independence at Lahore?",
    "answerText": " Lord Irwin"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87038,
    "questionText": " When was the first Atom Bomb exploded?",
    "answerText": 1945
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87039,
    "questionText": " In which year was the first General Elections (after independence) in India took place?",
    "answerText": 1952
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87040,
    "questionText": " In which year was China attacked India?",
    "answerText": 1962
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87041,
    "questionText": " In which year ``Quit India'' Movement was launched by Indian National Congress?",
    "answerText": 1942
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87042,
    "questionText": " Goa was liberated on?",
    "answerText": 1961
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87043,
    "questionText": " In which year did Asoka conquer Kalinga?",
    "answerText": " 261 BC"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87044,
    "questionText": " In which year was Bangladesh Liberated?",
    "answerText": 1971
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87045,
    "questionText": " In which year East India Company was established?",
    "answerText": " 1600 AD"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87046,
    "questionText": " In which year was Jesus Christ Born?",
    "answerText": " BC 4"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87047,
    "questionText": " Ajanta paintings depicts scenes from?",
    "answerText": " Jataka tales"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87048,
    "questionText": " In which year was Martin Luthar King Assassinated?",
    "answerText": 1968
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87049,
    "questionText": " Pushyabhuti dynasty ruled over?",
    "answerText": " Thaneswar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87050,
    "questionText": " The Aryan came to India from ......?",
    "answerText": " Central Asia"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87051,
    "questionText": " In which year Portuguese captured Goa?",
    "answerText": " 1510 AD"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87052,
    "questionText": " In which year was Jesus Christ Crucified?",
    "answerText": " 33 AD"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87053,
    "questionText": " The partition of Bengal was carried out under the rule of ............?",
    "answerText": " Lord Curzon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87054,
    "questionText": " Emperor Kanishka belonged to ........... dynasty?",
    "answerText": " Kushan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87055,
    "questionText": " Megasthenes visited India during the reign of?",
    "answerText": " Chandra Gupta Maurya"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87056,
    "questionText": " The first women ruler of Delhi was?",
    "answerText": " Razia Sultana"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87057,
    "questionText": " The Capital of Pallavas?",
    "answerText": " Kanchi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87058,
    "questionText": " Who was generally known as ``Indian Napolean''?",
    "answerText": " Samudragupta"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87059,
    "questionText": " Whose reign in Ancient India is known as ``The Golden Age''?",
    "answerText": " Shahjahan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87060,
    "questionText": " The Slogan ``Jai Jawan Jai Kisan'' was launched by whom?",
    "answerText": " Lal Bahadur Shastri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87061,
    "questionText": " The first Viceroy of India was....?",
    "answerText": " Lord Canning"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87062,
    "questionText": " Hampi was the Capital of......?",
    "answerText": " Vijayanagar Empire"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87063,
    "questionText": " The first partition of Bengal was held on?",
    "answerText": 1905
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87064,
    "questionText": " Who built the famous Taj Mahal in Agra?",
    "answerText": " Shahjahan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87065,
    "questionText": " Who founded Brahmo Samaj?",
    "answerText": " Rajaram Mohan Roy"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87066,
    "questionText": " In which year the first Sikh War took Place?",
    "answerText": 1845
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87067,
    "questionText": " In which year Tashket agreement was signed?",
    "answerText": 1966
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87068,
    "questionText": " In which year Alexander's Invasion of India took place?",
    "answerText": " 326 BC"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87069,
    "questionText": " In which year India was invaded by Timur?",
    "answerText": 1398
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87070,
    "questionText": " Who founded Vijayanagar empire?",
    "answerText": " Harihara and Bukka with the help of Saint Vidyaranya"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87071,
    "questionText": " Who founded Khilji Dynasty?",
    "answerText": " Jalaluddin Khilji"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87072,
    "questionText": " The fist battle of Panipat was fought between?",
    "answerText": " Baber and Ibrahim Lodhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87073,
    "questionText": " Who was the founder of Maurya dynasty?",
    "answerText": " Chandra Gupta Maurya"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87074,
    "questionText": " In which year The City of Amritsar was founded by Guru Ram Das, the 4th Sikh Guru?",
    "answerText": " 1577 AD"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87075,
    "questionText": " How many times did Muhammed Gazni invaded India?",
    "answerText": " 17 times"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87076,
    "questionText": " Who was the author of Aithihiamala?",
    "answerText": " Kottarathil Sankunni"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87077,
    "questionText": " During whose reign Tansen lived?",
    "answerText": " Akbar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87078,
    "questionText": " Who is called the ``Father of Indian Rupee''?",
    "answerText": " Shershah Suri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87079,
    "questionText": " The first Muslim Ruler in India to introduce the standing army was?",
    "answerText": " Ala -ud-din- khilji"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87080,
    "questionText": " Punjab was annexed to British territories in the year?",
    "answerText": 1849
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87081,
    "questionText": " Who was the founder of Great Magadha Empire?",
    "answerText": " Bimbisara"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87082,
    "questionText": " Buland Darwaza was built by Whom?",
    "answerText": " Akbar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87083,
    "questionText": " The title `Vikramaditya' was assumed by?",
    "answerText": " Chandra Gupta II"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87084,
    "questionText": " The transfer of Capital to Devagiri from Delhi by Mohammed Bin Tuglak had one good effect that is?",
    "answerText": " The country could now be governed from a central place"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87085,
    "questionText": " The most noteworthy difference between the Cholas and the other Indian rulers of the time is seen in?",
    "answerText": " Cholas encouragement to Local Self Government in Villages"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87086,
    "questionText": " Who was the last Hindu King of Northern India?",
    "answerText": " Harsha Vardhana"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87087,
    "questionText": " Railway was introduced in India by?",
    "answerText": " Lord Dalhousie"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87088,
    "questionText": " Who designed City of Chandigarh?",
    "answerText": " Le Corbousier"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87089,
    "questionText": " The first Women President of Indian National Congress?",
    "answerText": " Annie Besant"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87090,
    "questionText": " Who wrote National Anthem of India?",
    "answerText": " Rabindranath Tagore"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87091,
    "questionText": " Who gave the call Dilli Chalo''?",
    "answerText": " Subash Chandra Bose"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87092,
    "questionText": " Srikakulam is the Capital of which dynasty?",
    "answerText": " Satavahanas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87093,
    "questionText": " The author of Natyasastra''?",
    "answerText": " Bharathamuni"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87094,
    "questionText": " The famous Gayathri Manthram is in ....?",
    "answerText": " Rig Veda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87095,
    "questionText": " Who wrote Aryabhateeyam?",
    "answerText": " Aryabhatta"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87096,
    "questionText": " Call Him Ram, Rahim, Allah, Khuda, Hari, Govind but He is one'' Who proclaimed this?",
    "answerText": " Tulsi Das"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87097,
    "questionText": " The Grand Trunk Road was built by?",
    "answerText": " Sher shah Suri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87098,
    "questionText": " Megasthenes was the ambassador of?",
    "answerText": " Selecus Nikator"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87099,
    "questionText": " The battle of Plassey (1757) was fought between....?",
    "answerText": " Robert Clive and Siraj - ud- daulah"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87100,
    "questionText": " Kuchipudi'' dance form originated in?",
    "answerText": " Kuchelapuram in Andhra Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87101,
    "questionText": " Who founded the Sunga Dynasty?",
    "answerText": " Pushyamitra Sunga"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87102,
    "questionText": " Patanjali lived in whose Court?",
    "answerText": " Pushya Mitra's"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87103,
    "questionText": " Who is known as ``constantine of Budhism''?",
    "answerText": " Asoka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87104,
    "questionText": " Asoka was initiated to Budhism by whom?",
    "answerText": " Upagupta"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87105,
    "questionText": " The last ruler of Satavahana dynasty?",
    "answerText": " Yajnashri Satakarni"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87106,
    "questionText": " The Capital of Kanishka empire?",
    "answerText": " Peshawar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87107,
    "questionText": " Red Fort was built by whom?",
    "answerText": " Shah Jahan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87108,
    "questionText": " Which ruler of Gupta Dynasty adopted the name Maharajadhiraja''?",
    "answerText": " Chandragupta I"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87109,
    "questionText": " The Allahabad Pillar inscription composed by Harisena Contain.........?",
    "answerText": " Informations about samudhragupta's conquest"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87110,
    "questionText": " Who gave Raja Ram Mohan Roy the title Raja''?",
    "answerText": " Akbar Shah II"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87111,
    "questionText": " Famous Ayurveda Physician of Gupta Age?",
    "answerText": " Dhanvanthari"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87112,
    "questionText": " The World famous universities Nalanda and Taxila'' belongs to ....... period?",
    "answerText": " Gupta"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87113,
    "questionText": " Who is popular by the names Indian Shakespeare and Prince of Indian Poets?",
    "answerText": " Kalidasa"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87114,
    "questionText": " The government emblem of Gupta dynasty?",
    "answerText": " Garuda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87115,
    "questionText": " The Huna king Mihirakula's Capital?",
    "answerText": " Sialkot"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87116,
    "questionText": " Who built Shiva Temple at Tanjavur?",
    "answerText": " Raja Raja Chola"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87117,
    "questionText": " Pulikeshin II was the most famous ruler of .....dynasty?",
    "answerText": " Chalukya Dynasty"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87118,
    "questionText": " The last Hindu king of Delhi?",
    "answerText": " Prithviraj Chauhan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87119,
    "questionText": " Who was the founder of Pallava Dynasty?",
    "answerText": " Simha Vishnu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87120,
    "questionText": " The Kailashnath Temple at Ellora was built by...?",
    "answerText": " Krishna I of Rashtrakuta dynasty"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87121,
    "questionText": " The pala dynasty was founded by whom?",
    "answerText": " Gopala"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87122,
    "questionText": " The Brihadeswara Temple at Tanjaore was built by whom?",
    "answerText": " Raja Raja Chola"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87123,
    "questionText": " Which ruler adopted the title ``Gangaikonda Chola''?",
    "answerText": " Rajendra I of chola dynasty"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87124,
    "questionText": " Who wrote Tamil Ramayana?",
    "answerText": " Kambar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87125,
    "questionText": " The Hoysala dynasty (1027-1343) was founded by whom?",
    "answerText": " Nripakama"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87126,
    "questionText": " Who wrote Raja Tarangini?",
    "answerText": " Kalhana"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87127,
    "questionText": " The chola ruler who founded the city of Kaveripatnam?",
    "answerText": " Karikala Chola"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87128,
    "questionText": " Who wrote Budha Charitha, Sutralankar and Saundrananda?",
    "answerText": " Aswaghosha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87129,
    "questionText": " The famous buddhist monk who propound the famous philosophy of `Madhyamika'?",
    "answerText": " Nagarju"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87130,
    "questionText": " In which year Pradhan Mantri Adarsh Gram Yojana was launched?",
    "answerText": 2010
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87131,
    "questionText": " The shelter home launched by Kudumbasree for women and children who are victims of atrocities?",
    "answerText": " Snehitha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87132,
    "questionText": " Which is the other name of Rajiv Gandhi Scheme for Empowerment of Adolescent Girls?",
    "answerText": " Sabala"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87133,
    "questionText": " In which year National Rural Employment Programme (NREP) was launched?",
    "answerText": 1980
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87134,
    "questionText": " What is the aim of Pradhan Mantri Awas Yojana?",
    "answerText": " To enable better living and drive economic growth stressing on the need for people centric urban planning and development."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87135,
    "questionText": " At which place Prime Minister Narendra Modi officially lauched the Standup India Scheme on 5th April 2016?",
    "answerText": " Noida"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87136,
    "questionText": " Swachch Bharat Abhiyan was started in which year?",
    "answerText": " 2014 (October 2)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87137,
    "questionText": " In which schedule of the Constitution Panchayat Raj is included?",
    "answerText": 11
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87138,
    "questionText": " What is the aim of Digital India?",
    "answerText": " Connecting rural areas with high-speed Internet networks and improving digital literacy."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87139,
    "questionText": " The Project started by the Government of Kerala to detect missing children?",
    "answerText": " Operation Valsalya"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87140,
    "questionText": " Name the organizations that provide support to Nadia district to construct toilet in all houses?",
    "answerText": " World Bank and UNICEF"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87141,
    "questionText": " Brand Ambassador of Make in Kerala?",
    "answerText": " Mammootty"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87142,
    "questionText": " The rehabilitation scheme launched by Kudumbasree aiming at poorest destitutes of the society?",
    "answerText": " Aasraya"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87143,
    "questionText": " In which year Valmiki Ambedkar Awaas Yojana was introduced?",
    "answerText": 2001
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87144,
    "questionText": " Which Department launched Indra Dhanush?",
    "answerText": " Health Ministry of the Union Government"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87145,
    "questionText": " Name the Prime Minister who appointed Ashok Mehta Committee in 1977?",
    "answerText": " Morarji Desai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87146,
    "questionText": " In which year Swabhiman was launched?",
    "answerText": " 2011(feb 15)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87147,
    "questionText": " The initiative of the Central Government as a part of the Startup India campaign to create 2.5 lakh SC/ST entrepreneurs?",
    "answerText": " Standup India"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87148,
    "questionText": " Which scheme replaced Aajeevika?",
    "answerText": " Deen Dayal Upadhyaya Antyodaya Yojana"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87149,
    "questionText": " Which five year plan was called Mahalanobis model?",
    "answerText": " Second"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87150,
    "questionText": " Who was the exponent of Sreeniketan Project?",
    "answerText": " Rabindranath Tagore"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87151,
    "questionText": " The brand Ambassador of Pradhan Mantri Jan Dhan Yojana?",
    "answerText": " Amitabh Bachan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87152,
    "questionText": " The brand ambassador of Nirmal Bharat Abhiyan?",
    "answerText": " Vidya Balan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87153,
    "questionText": " In which year Family Planning was started in India?",
    "answerText": 1952
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87154,
    "questionText": " Who served as the chairperson of Planning Board for the longest period?",
    "answerText": " Indira Gandhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87155,
    "questionText": " In which year Pradhan Mantri Suraksha Yojana was launched?",
    "answerText": 2015
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87156,
    "questionText": " When was DD Kisan was launched by Prime Minister Narendra Modi?",
    "answerText": " 2015 May 26"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87157,
    "questionText": " Who called villages as ‘Little republics’?",
    "answerText": " Charles Metcaf"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87158,
    "questionText": " In India, Community Development Project was started in?",
    "answerText": " October 2; 1952"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87159,
    "questionText": " In which Panchayat Athulyam was launched for the first time?",
    "answerText": " Nilambur (Malappuram)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87160,
    "questionText": " The name of te scheme to provide Health insurance to poor (BPL), Domestic workers, MGNERGA workers, Rikshawpullers, Building and other construction workers, and many other categories as may be identified by the respective states?",
    "answerText": " Rashtriya Swasthya Bheema Yojana"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87161,
    "questionText": " On 30th April 2015 which was declared as the first open defacation free district in India?",
    "answerText": " Nadia (West Bengal)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87162,
    "questionText": " In which year Swarna Jayanti Grama Swarozgar Yojana (SGSY) was started?",
    "answerText": 1999
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87163,
    "questionText": " Who inauguarated Kudumbasree Project at Malappuram?",
    "answerText": " AB Vajpayee"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87164,
    "questionText": " The Cochlear Implantation Project lauched by Kerala Government?",
    "answerText": " Sruthitharangam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87165,
    "questionText": " The period of the first Five Year Plan?",
    "answerText": " 1951-56"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87166,
    "questionText": " The Panchayat Raj system was introduced in 1959 under the recommendation of which committee?",
    "answerText": " Belwant Rai Mehta Committee"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87167,
    "questionText": " Under which name Nirmal Bharat Abhiyan was restructured?",
    "answerText": " Swachch Bharat Abhiyan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87168,
    "questionText": " Who was the exponent of Marthandom Project?",
    "answerText": " Spencer Hatch"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87169,
    "questionText": " Whose birth day is observed as Antyodaya Day (Sepemtember 25)?",
    "answerText": " Deen Dayal Upadyaya"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87170,
    "questionText": " In which year National Rural Employment Guarentee Programme (NREGP) was brought into effect?",
    "answerText": 2005
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87171,
    "questionText": " Who launched Sevagram Project?",
    "answerText": " Gandhiji"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87172,
    "questionText": " Employment Assurance Scheme (EAS) was launched in which year?",
    "answerText": 1993
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87173,
    "questionText": " What is the other name of National Rural Livelihood Mission?",
    "answerText": " Ajeevika"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87174,
    "questionText": " Who designed Swachch Bharat Mission logo?",
    "answerText": " Anant Khasbardar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87175,
    "questionText": " Which five year plan was suffered by the Chinese attack of 1962?",
    "answerText": " Third"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87176,
    "questionText": " Annual Plans are implemented for the first time during the period?",
    "answerText": " 1966-69"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87177,
    "questionText": " In which year Jeevan Pramaan was launched?",
    "answerText": 2014
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87178,
    "questionText": " What is the aim of the Growth rate of 12th Five Year Plan?",
    "answerText": " Eight"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87179,
    "questionText": " When the Digital India Project was started?",
    "answerText": " 2015 July 1"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87180,
    "questionText": " During which Five Year Plan Khadi and Village Industries Commission was set up?",
    "answerText": " Second"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87181,
    "questionText": " In which list of the Constitution ‘Economic and Social Planning’ is included?",
    "answerText": " Concurrent"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87182,
    "questionText": " Who gave the concept of PURA (Providing Urban Amenities to Rural Areas)?",
    "answerText": " APJ Abdul Kalam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87183,
    "questionText": " Who is the custodian of Digital India Project?",
    "answerText": " National Optical Fibre Network"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87184,
    "questionText": " Father of Family Planning in India?",
    "answerText": " RD Karve"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87185,
    "questionText": " The Integrated Rural Development Programme was started during which Five Year Plan?",
    "answerText": " Sixth"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87186,
    "questionText": " Who designed Make in India Campaign?",
    "answerText": " Wieden+Kennedy"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87187,
    "questionText": " In which year Accessible India Campaign or Sugamya Bharat Abhiyan was launched?",
    "answerText": 2016
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87188,
    "questionText": " Where Farkha Development Scheme was introduced?",
    "answerText": " Madras"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87189,
    "questionText": " During which Five Year Plan stresswas by laid on employment, poverty alleviation, and justice.?",
    "answerText": " Fifth"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87190,
    "questionText": " The first state to achieve total primary education?",
    "answerText": " Kerala"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87191,
    "questionText": " The sheme for providing One-time cash incentive to pregnant women for institutional/ home births through skilled assistance?",
    "answerText": " Janani Suraksha Yojana"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87192,
    "questionText": " Who said ‘India lives in her villages’?",
    "answerText": " Gandhiji"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87193,
    "questionText": " Who was the last Deputy Chairman of Planning Commission?",
    "answerText": " Montek Singh Ahluwalia"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87194,
    "questionText": " The ex-officio chairman of the Planning Commission was?",
    "answerText": " Prime Minister"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87195,
    "questionText": " Which was the first state to enact an employment guarantee act in the 1970s?",
    "answerText": " Maharashtra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87196,
    "questionText": " Marthandom Project was launched in the state of?",
    "answerText": " Tamil Nadu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87197,
    "questionText": " In which year Jawahar Rozgar Yojana (JRY) was started?",
    "answerText": 1989
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87198,
    "questionText": " Districts where Mahathma Gandhi National Employment Guarentee Programme implemented for the first time in Kerala?",
    "answerText": " Palakkad and Wayanad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87199,
    "questionText": " The chairman of the National Development Council was?",
    "answerText": " Prime Minister"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87200,
    "questionText": " The exponent of Ittawa Project?",
    "answerText": " Albert Mayer"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87201,
    "questionText": " The aim of Ujjwala Project launched by Union Government?",
    "answerText": " Rehabilitation of sexually abused victims"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87202,
    "questionText": " Who is the Chairperson of Kudumbasree?",
    "answerText": " Minister for Local Self Government"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87203,
    "questionText": " National Pension Scheme was launched in which year?",
    "answerText": 2004
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87204,
    "questionText": " What is the aim of Indra Dhanush?",
    "answerText": " Provide vaccination against seven diseases"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87205,
    "questionText": " Who was the exponent of Gandhian Plan?",
    "answerText": " Sreeman Narayanan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87206,
    "questionText": " The Project started by the Government of Kerala to provide special care to children whose parents are affected by HIV?",
    "answerText": " Snehapoorvam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87207,
    "questionText": " In which year Social Welfare Department was started in Kerala?",
    "answerText": 1975
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87208,
    "questionText": " Union Goverments scheme for the welfare of non resident Indians?",
    "answerText": " Mahathma Gandhi Pravasi Suraksha Yojana"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87209,
    "questionText": " In which year Sreeniketan Project was launched?",
    "answerText": 1914
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87210,
    "questionText": " Which scheme was replaced by Pradhan Mantri Jan Dhan Yojana?",
    "answerText": " Swabhiman"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87211,
    "questionText": " Who designed Aadhar logo?",
    "answerText": " Atul Pandey"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87212,
    "questionText": " In which year Command Area Development Programme was launched?",
    "answerText": 1974
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87213,
    "questionText": " The Act to provide legal guarantee for one hundred days of employment in every financial year to adult members of any rural household willing to do public work-related unskilled manual work?",
    "answerText": " Mahatma Gandhi National Rural Employment Guarantee Act"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87214,
    "questionText": " In which year Rashtriya Swasthya Bheema Yojana was launched?",
    "answerText": 2008
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87215,
    "questionText": " The new form of Jawaharlal Nehru Urban Renewal Mission?",
    "answerText": " AMRUT (Atal Mission for Rejuvanation and Urban Transformation Scheme)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87216,
    "questionText": " Father of Local Self Government in India?",
    "answerText": " Lord Rippon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87217,
    "questionText": " Name the project launched by Literacy Mission to achieve total primary education?",
    "answerText": " Athulyam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87218,
    "questionText": " Who was the Prime Minister of India when the 73rd and 74th Amendments of the Constitution were passed?",
    "answerText": " Narasimha Raosident of India"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87219,
    "questionText": " Who was the Prime Minister when Digital India was launched?",
    "answerText": " Narendra Modi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87220,
    "questionText": " Where Valmiki Ambedkar Awaaz Yojana was inaugurated?",
    "answerText": " Hyderabad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87221,
    "questionText": " In which year Sampoorna Grameen Rozgar Yojana (SGRY) was launched?",
    "answerText": 2001
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87222,
    "questionText": " Community Development Programme was introduced in India in?",
    "answerText": 1952
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87223,
    "questionText": " The first chairman of Planning Commission was?",
    "answerText": " Jawaharlal Nehru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87224,
    "questionText": " The aim of Deen Dayal Upadhyaya Gram Jyoti Yojana?",
    "answerText": " Rural power supply"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87225,
    "questionText": " In which year Kudumbasree Project was inaugurated?",
    "answerText": 1998
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87226,
    "questionText": " The main objective of Prime Minister’s Grama Sadak Yojana (PMGSY)?",
    "answerText": " To construct all weather roads to connect hilly areas and main roads"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87227,
    "questionText": " The main model that formed the basis of the strategy of the Second Five Year Plan was formulated by whom?",
    "answerText": " P.C.Mahalanobis"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87228,
    "questionText": " In which year Sukanya Samridhi Yojana (Girl Child Prosperity Scheme) was launched?",
    "answerText": 2015
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87229,
    "questionText": " In which year Indra Dhanush Sceheme launched?",
    "answerText": " 2014 (December 25)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87230,
    "questionText": " What is the annual premium of Pradhan Mantri Jeevan Jyothi Bheema Yojana (PMJJBY)?",
    "answerText": " Rs 330"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87231,
    "questionText": " The first deputy chairman of Planning Commission was?",
    "answerText": " Gulsarilal Nanda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87232,
    "questionText": " In which year Rashtriya Krishi Vikas Yojana was started?",
    "answerText": 2007
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87233,
    "questionText": " In which year Rural Landless Employment Guarentee Programme (RLEGP) was introduced?",
    "answerText": " 1983-84"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87234,
    "questionText": " NRY (Nehru Rozgar Yojana) was started in which year?",
    "answerText": 1989
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87235,
    "questionText": " In which area priority was given in the second Five year Plan?",
    "answerText": " Industries"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87236,
    "questionText": " Who is the ambassador of She Taxi?",
    "answerText": " Manju Warrier"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87237,
    "questionText": " The Project started by the Government of Kerala to address the problems of unmarried mothers?",
    "answerText": " Snehasparsham"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87238,
    "questionText": " The elections to the three- tier Panchayat Raj institutions are conducted by?",
    "answerText": " State Election Commission"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87239,
    "questionText": " In which year National Social Assistance Scheme was launched?",
    "answerText": 1995
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87240,
    "questionText": " Where EMS Housing Scheme was launched for the first time?",
    "answerText": " Kodakara (Thrissur)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87241,
    "questionText": " In which year Aam Aadmi Bheema Yojana was started?",
    "answerText": 2013
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87242,
    "questionText": " The motto of National e-Governance Plan?",
    "answerText": " Public Services Closer Home"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87243,
    "questionText": " In which year Deen Dayal Upadhyaya Antyodaya Yojana was launched?",
    "answerText": 2014
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87244,
    "questionText": " The Project started by the Government of Kerala to provide monthly financial assistance to bedridden patients?",
    "answerText": " Aaswasakiran"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87245,
    "questionText": " What is the aim of Pradhan Mantri Jan Dhan Yojana?",
    "answerText": " To make banking facility available to all citizens"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87246,
    "questionText": " The major source of revenue of the state governments?",
    "answerText": " Sales Tax"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87247,
    "questionText": " The concept of mixed economy was introduced during which Five Year Plan?",
    "answerText": " Second"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87248,
    "questionText": " The name of strategic and customer-oriented initiative of the Government of India to modernize India’s Ports?",
    "answerText": " Sagarmala Project"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87249,
    "questionText": " In which year Pradhanmantri Grama Sadak Yojana was started?",
    "answerText": 2000
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87250,
    "questionText": " The Aadhar based Digital Life Certificate for Pensioners is known as?",
    "answerText": " Jeevan Pramaan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87251,
    "questionText": " What percent is the Swachch Bharat cess?",
    "answerText": 0.005
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87252,
    "questionText": " In which year Pradhan Mantri Jeevan Jyoti Bheema Yojana was launched?",
    "answerText": 2015
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87253,
    "questionText": " Which Article of the Constitution is related to Village Panchayats?",
    "answerText": 40
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87254,
    "questionText": " When was Sansad Adarsh Gram Yojana was started?",
    "answerText": " 2014 October 11"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87255,
    "questionText": " Where Sreeniketan Project was launched?",
    "answerText": " Bengal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87256,
    "questionText": " Sevagram is now in the state of?",
    "answerText": " Maharashtra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87257,
    "questionText": " On which date Planning Commission came into existence?",
    "answerText": " 15th March;1950"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87258,
    "questionText": " What is the new name of Social Welfare Department in Kerala?",
    "answerText": " Social Justice Department"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87259,
    "questionText": " Where the Gurgaon Project was launched?",
    "answerText": " Punjab"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87260,
    "questionText": " The first Minister for Community Development in the Central Cabinet?",
    "answerText": " S.K.Dey"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87261,
    "questionText": " In which year Drought Prone Area Programme was introduced?",
    "answerText": 1973
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87262,
    "questionText": " The period of second Five year Plan?",
    "answerText": " 1956-61"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87263,
    "questionText": " In which year Antyodaya Anna Yojana was started?",
    "answerText": 2000
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87264,
    "questionText": " In which year Janani Suraksha Yojana was launched?",
    "answerText": 2005
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87265,
    "questionText": " In which year Integrated Rural Development Programme (IRDP) was launched?",
    "answerText": 1980
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87266,
    "questionText": " Rajiv Gandhi Grameen Vidyutikaran Yojana launched in 2005 was replaced by which scheme?",
    "answerText": " Deen Dayal Upadhyaya Gram Jyoti Yojana"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87267,
    "questionText": " Who coined the term ‘Hindu Growth Rate’?",
    "answerText": " Raj Krishna"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87268,
    "questionText": " Who inaugurated the Panchayat Raj system at Nagaur in Rajastan in 1959?",
    "answerText": " Jawaharlal Nehru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87269,
    "questionText": " Atal Pension Yojana was started in which year?",
    "answerText": 2015
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87270,
    "questionText": " The number of cities included in the first phase of AMRUT?",
    "answerText": 500
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87271,
    "questionText": " In which year Smart Cities Mision was launched?",
    "answerText": 2015
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87272,
    "questionText": " The service started by Kudumbasree for the safe travelling of women?",
    "answerText": " Kudumbasree Travels"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87273,
    "questionText": " Where is the headquarters of CAPART (Council for Advancedment of People’s Action and Rural Technology)?",
    "answerText": " New Delhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87274,
    "questionText": " Which project provides ‘108 Ambulance’ Service?",
    "answerText": " National Rural Health Mission"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87275,
    "questionText": " In which year Nirbhaya was started?",
    "answerText": 2013
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87276,
    "questionText": " Who is the brand ambassador of Athulyam Project?",
    "answerText": " Dileep"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87277,
    "questionText": " The concept of Five Year Plan in India was introduced by?",
    "answerText": " Jawaharlal Nehru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87278,
    "questionText": " Which District in Haryana awarded for being the top performing district in the state under the Digital India campaign on 28th December 2015?",
    "answerText": " Panchkula"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87279,
    "questionText": " Which one of the ancient dynasties was famous for village administration?",
    "answerText": " Chola"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87280,
    "questionText": " Who is called as the father of Planning in India?",
    "answerText": " M Visweswaraiah"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87281,
    "questionText": " What is the aim of Smart Cities Mision?",
    "answerText": " To enable better living and drive economic growth stressing on the need for people centric urban planning and development."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87282,
    "questionText": " The Prime Minister who started Antyodaya Anna Yojana?",
    "answerText": " AB Vajpayee"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87283,
    "questionText": " Bharatmala Project aims the development of?",
    "answerText": " Roads"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87284,
    "questionText": " The taxi service for women started by Social Justice Department of Government of Kerala?",
    "answerText": " She Taxi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87285,
    "questionText": " The scheme of Kerala Government to encourage donation of organs?",
    "answerText": " Mrithasanjeevani"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87286,
    "questionText": " In which year Indira Gandhi Matritva Sahyog Yojana was launched?",
    "answerText": 2010
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87287,
    "questionText": " The father of Nilokheri Experiment?",
    "answerText": " SK Dey"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87288,
    "questionText": " In which year Pradhan Mantri Awas Yojana was launched?",
    "answerText": 2015
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87289,
    "questionText": " Brand Ambassador of Digital India Project?",
    "answerText": " Kriti Tiwari"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87290,
    "questionText": " What is the motto of Digital India?",
    "answerText": " Power to Empower"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87291,
    "questionText": " Who designed Digital India logo?",
    "answerText": " Rana Bhowmik"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87292,
    "questionText": " Which five year plan was terminated prematurely by the Janata Government of Morarji Desai in 1978?",
    "answerText": " Fifth"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87293,
    "questionText": " In which year TRYSEM (Training of Rural Youth for Self Employment) was launched?",
    "answerText": 1979
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87294,
    "questionText": " Who was the architect of Gurgaon Project?",
    "answerText": " FL Brane"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87295,
    "questionText": " The Project started by the Government of Kerala to provide treatment to children suffering from fatal diseases?",
    "answerText": " Thalolam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87296,
    "questionText": " The slogan of Swachch Bharat Abhiyan(Clean India Mission)?",
    "answerText": " One step towards cleanliness"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87297,
    "questionText": " In which year Marginal Farmers and Agricultural Labourers Development Agency was formed?",
    "answerText": 1975
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87298,
    "questionText": " The first district to attain total primary education?",
    "answerText": " Kannur (Second Kasargod)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87299,
    "questionText": " In which year Food For Work Pragramme was started?",
    "answerText": 1977
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87300,
    "questionText": " In which schedule of the constitution provisions related to Municipal Administration is included?",
    "answerText": 12
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87301,
    "questionText": " The first television channels for farmers in India?",
    "answerText": " DD Kisan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87302,
    "questionText": " The father of the idea of ‘Gram Swaraj’?",
    "answerText": " Gandhiji"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87303,
    "questionText": " The 73rd Amendment of the constitution came into force in?",
    "answerText": 1993
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87304,
    "questionText": " In which year Employment Assurance Scheme (EAS) was started?",
    "answerText": 1993
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87305,
    "questionText": " The aim of Make in Kerala?",
    "answerText": " To make Kerala investment friendly"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87306,
    "questionText": " When Nirmal Bharat Abhiyan was started?",
    "answerText": 1999
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87307,
    "questionText": " What was the aim of Rashtriya Krishi Vikas Yojana?",
    "answerText": " Achieve 4% annual growth in agriculture through development of Agriculture and its allied sectors during the XI Plan period"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87308,
    "questionText": " The scheme of Government of India that primarily ensures equitable share to a girl child in resources and savings of a family in which she is generally discriminated as against a male child?",
    "answerText": " Sukanya Samridhi Yojana"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87309,
    "questionText": " Farkha Development Scheme was introduced in the year?",
    "answerText": 1946
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87310,
    "questionText": " The Project started by the Government of Kerala to curb atrocities against women and girls?",
    "answerText": " Nirbhaya"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87311,
    "questionText": " In which year Ganga Kalyan Yojana was launched?",
    "answerText": 1997
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87312,
    "questionText": " During which Five Year Plan Bharat Nirman Project was inaugurated?",
    "answerText": " Tenth"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87313,
    "questionText": " Name the project launched by Kerala Government in the lines of Mahathma Gandhi National Employment Guarentee Programme for provide employment to unskilled urban people for atleast 100 days?",
    "answerText": " Ayyankali Urban Employment Guarentee Scheme"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87314,
    "questionText": " Where Mahathma Gandhi National Employment Guarentee Programme was started for the first time?",
    "answerText": " Bandlappalli in Andhra Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87315,
    "questionText": " Ittawa Project was launched in the year?",
    "answerText": 1948
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87316,
    "questionText": " Who inauguarated Swachch Bharat Abhiyan by cleaning Rajpath in New Delhi?",
    "answerText": " Narendra Modi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87317,
    "questionText": " What is the aim of Accessible India Campaign or Sugamya Bharat Abhiyan?",
    "answerText": " To make government buildings disabled friendly"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87318,
    "questionText": " On which date Make in India was declared?",
    "answerText": " 2014 September 25"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87319,
    "questionText": " In which year Development of Women and Children in rural Area (DWCRA) was launched?",
    "answerText": " 1983-84"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87320,
    "questionText": " In 1938, the National Planning Committee of Indian National Congress was set up under the chairmanship of?",
    "answerText": " Jawaharlal Nehru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87321,
    "questionText": " Which animal can be seen in the logo of Make in India Campaign?",
    "answerText": " Lion"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87322,
    "questionText": " Who declared Kerala as the first Indian state to achieve total primary education on 13th January 2016?",
    "answerText": " Vice President Hamid Ansari"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87323,
    "questionText": " Name the campaign that was first announced by Prime Minister Narendra Modi in his Independence Day address from the Red Fort in 2015?",
    "answerText": " Startup India Campaign"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87324,
    "questionText": " In which year Jawahar Gramasamridhi Yojana (JGSY) was started?",
    "answerText": 1999
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87325,
    "questionText": " What is the annual premium of Pradhan Mantri Suraksha Bheema Yojana (PMSBY)?",
    "answerText": " Rs 12"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87326,
    "questionText": " In which state Community Development Programme was started in an experimental basis?",
    "answerText": " Punjab"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87327,
    "questionText": " The number of cities included in the first phase of Smart City Project?",
    "answerText": 100
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87328,
    "questionText": " In which year Indira Awaas Yojana (IAY) was introduced?",
    "answerText": 1985
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87329,
    "questionText": " In which district Operation Sulaimani implemented for the first time?",
    "answerText": " Kozhikode"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87330,
    "questionText": " In which year Mahila Samridhi Yojana was introduced?",
    "answerText": 1993
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87331,
    "questionText": " The online scheme of Union Government to book new LPG connection?",
    "answerText": " Sahaj"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87332,
    "questionText": " Which is the first smart city allotted to Kerala?",
    "answerText": " Kochi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87333,
    "questionText": " What is the aim of Deen Dayal Upadhyaya Gram Jyoti Yojana?",
    "answerText": " Creation of Rural Electricity Infrastructure & Household Electrification for providing access to electricity to rural households"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87334,
    "questionText": " Where Ittawa Project was implemented?",
    "answerText": " Uttar Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87335,
    "questionText": " The date on which Swachch Bharat cess was brought into effect?",
    "answerText": " 2015 November 15"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87336,
    "questionText": " In which year Annapoorna Scheme was launched?",
    "answerText": 2000
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87337,
    "questionText": " In which year Nehru Rozgar Yojana (NRY) was started?",
    "answerText": 1989
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87338,
    "questionText": " Which year National Initiative on Climate Resilient Agriculture was launched?",
    "answerText": 2011
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87339,
    "questionText": " During which Five Year Plan Food for Work Programme was introduced?",
    "answerText": " Fifth Plan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87340,
    "questionText": " In which year Gramin Bhandaran Yojana was launched?",
    "answerText": 2007
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87341,
    "questionText": " In which year Ashok Mehta Committee was appointed?",
    "answerText": 1977
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87342,
    "questionText": " Marthandom Project was started in the year?",
    "answerText": 1921
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87343,
    "questionText": " Who was the Prime Minister of India when Make in India Campaign was launched?",
    "answerText": " Narendra Modi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87344,
    "questionText": " In which year Small Farmers Development Agency was formed?",
    "answerText": 1971
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87345,
    "questionText": " The Indira Awas Yojana aims to provide?",
    "answerText": " Houses to poor"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87346,
    "questionText": " In which year Prime Minister’s Rozgar Yojana was started?",
    "answerText": 1993
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87347,
    "questionText": " The Parliament of India consists of?",
    "answerText": " Lok Sabha; Rajya Sabha; President"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87348,
    "questionText": " The Parliament building of India was designed by?",
    "answerText": " Edwin Lutuens and Herbert Baker"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87349,
    "questionText": " Lok Sabha is also known as?",
    "answerText": " House of People"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87350,
    "questionText": " The maximum number of members that can be nominated by the president to the Lok Sabha from Anglo Indian community?",
    "answerText": 2
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87351,
    "questionText": " The total number of members of Parliament at present?",
    "answerText": 790
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87352,
    "questionText": " Who presides over the Lok Sabha?",
    "answerText": " Speaker"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87353,
    "questionText": " Who presides over the joint sitting of Parliament?",
    "answerText": " Speaker of Lok Sabha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87354,
    "questionText": " The quorum of for the meeting of either house of Parliament?",
    "answerText": " 1/10th of the total members of the house"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87355,
    "questionText": " The minimum age required to become a member of Lok Sabha?",
    "answerText": 25
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87356,
    "questionText": " The tenure of member of Lok Sabha is ...... years?",
    "answerText": 5
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87357,
    "questionText": " As per the provisions of the Constitution the number of members of Lok Sabha is limited as?",
    "answerText": 552
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87358,
    "questionText": " The total number of nominated members in Parliament?",
    "answerText": 14
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87359,
    "questionText": " The number of elected members in Lok Sabha at present?",
    "answerText": 543
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87360,
    "questionText": " The members of the Union Cabinet is collectively responsible to?",
    "answerText": " Lok Sabha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87361,
    "questionText": " According to the Constitution the maximum limit of the number of members can be elected from States?",
    "answerText": 530
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87362,
    "questionText": " According to the Constitution the maximum limit of the number of members can be elected from Union Territoties?",
    "answerText": 20
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87363,
    "questionText": " The number of sessions of Lok Sabha take place in a year?",
    "answerText": 3
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87364,
    "questionText": " The longest session of Lok Sabha?",
    "answerText": " Budget session"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87365,
    "questionText": " The structure of the Parliament building of India?",
    "answerText": " Circular"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87366,
    "questionText": " The colour of the carpet in Lok Sabha?",
    "answerText": " Green"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87367,
    "questionText": " The total number of elected members in Parliament at present?",
    "answerText": 776
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87368,
    "questionText": " As per constitutional provisions the maximum number of members in Parliament is limited as?",
    "answerText": 802
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87369,
    "questionText": " On normal business days, the Lok Sabha proceedings starts at ...... a.m?",
    "answerText": 11
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87370,
    "questionText": " The first hour of every sitting of Lok Sabha is called the .......?",
    "answerText": " Question Hour"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87371,
    "questionText": " The minimum age required to vote in Lok Sabha elections?",
    "answerText": 18
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87372,
    "questionText": " The tenure of member of Rajya Sabha is ...... years.?",
    "answerText": 6
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87373,
    "questionText": " Rajya Sabha is also known as?",
    "answerText": " Council of States"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87374,
    "questionText": " How many members are nominated by the president to the Rajya Sabha?",
    "answerText": 12
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87375,
    "questionText": " The number of elected members in Rajya Sabha at present?",
    "answerText": 233
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87376,
    "questionText": " Who was known as ‘father of Rajya Sabha’?",
    "answerText": " S. Radhakrishnan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87377,
    "questionText": " The first chairman of Rajya Sabha?",
    "answerText": " S. Radhakrishnan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87378,
    "questionText": " The first Deputy Chairman of Rajya Sabha?",
    "answerText": " S.V. Krishnamurthy"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87379,
    "questionText": " As per the provisions of the Constitution the number of members of Rajya Sabha is limited as?",
    "answerText": 250
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87380,
    "questionText": " Who presides over the Rajya Sabha?",
    "answerText": " Vice President"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87381,
    "questionText": " Name the Union Territories that are represented in Rajya Sabha?",
    "answerText": " Delhi and Puducherry"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87382,
    "questionText": " Which Union territory has the largest number of members in Rajya Sabha?",
    "answerText": " Delhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87383,
    "questionText": " Which State has the largest number of members in Rajya Sabha?",
    "answerText": " U.P."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87384,
    "questionText": " The minimum age required to become a member of Rajya Sabha?",
    "answerText": 30
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87385,
    "questionText": " The colour of the carpet in Rajya Sabha?",
    "answerText": " Red"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87386,
    "questionText": " Rajya Sabha was formed on 3rd April, ........?",
    "answerText": 1952
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87387,
    "questionText": " The number of indirectly elected members to the Rajya Sabha from states?",
    "answerText": 229
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87388,
    "questionText": " The number of indirectly elected members to the Rajya Sabha from Union Territories?",
    "answerText": 4
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87389,
    "questionText": " The total number of members in the Rajya Sabha at present?",
    "answerText": 245
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87390,
    "questionText": " How much of the total members of Rajya Sabha is elected every two years?",
    "answerText": " 1/3rd of total members"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87391,
    "questionText": " Which house of Parliament is presided over by a non-member?",
    "answerText": " Rajya Sabha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87392,
    "questionText": " Which is called House of Elders?",
    "answerText": " Rajya Sabha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87393,
    "questionText": " A money bill sent to Rajya Sabha should be returned to the lower house within ...... days?",
    "answerText": 14
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87394,
    "questionText": " The date mentioned in the preamble of the Constitution?",
    "answerText": " 26th November 1949"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87395,
    "questionText": " The status of India from 15th August 1947 to 26th January 1950?",
    "answerText": " Dominion in the British Commonwealth of Nations"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87396,
    "questionText": " “The state shall have no religion of its own and all persons shall be equally entilted to freedom of conscience and right freely to profess, practice and propagate religion”- This principle is termed?",
    "answerText": " Secularism"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87397,
    "questionText": " The first joint sitting of Lok Sabha and Rajya Sabha was held in the year?",
    "answerText": 1961
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87398,
    "questionText": " The objective resolution was adopted by the Constituent Assembly on?",
    "answerText": " 22nd January 1947"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87399,
    "questionText": " The sovereignty under the Constitution of India vested with?",
    "answerText": " People"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87400,
    "questionText": " Which part of the Constitution of India represent the quintessence, the philosophy and the ideals or soul of the Constitution?",
    "answerText": " Preamble"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87401,
    "questionText": " “A representative and responsible system under which those who administer the affairs of the state are chosen by the electorate and accountable to them”- This refers to?",
    "answerText": " Democracy"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87402,
    "questionText": " Which term implies an elected head of state?",
    "answerText": " Republic"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87403,
    "questionText": " The member of the Constituent Assembly who made the remark that “The Preamble is the most precious part of the Constitution. It is the soul of the Constitution. It is the key to the Constitution”?",
    "answerText": " Thakurdas Bhargava"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87404,
    "questionText": " Who made the statement “The Preamble of the Constitution is the horoscope of our Sovereign Democratic Republic”?",
    "answerText": " K.M. Munshi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87405,
    "questionText": " In which case the Supreme Court gave the verdict that the preamble is a part of Constitution?",
    "answerText": " Keshavananda Bharati Case"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87406,
    "questionText": " The words ‘Unity of the Nation’ in the preamble was substituted by ....... through the 42nd Amendment?",
    "answerText": " Unity and Integrity of the Nation"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87407,
    "questionText": " In which year preamble was amended?",
    "answerText": 1976
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87408,
    "questionText": " The idea of council of ministers are collectively responsible to the lower house of the Parliament has been copied from?",
    "answerText": " Britain"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87409,
    "questionText": " The feature of Federal Scheme has been borrowed from?",
    "answerText": " Govt of India Act; 1935"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87410,
    "questionText": " The post of speaker of Lok Sabha has been copied from?",
    "answerText": " Britain"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87411,
    "questionText": " Which amendment amended the preamble?",
    "answerText": " 42nd"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87412,
    "questionText": " നാഷണൽ റിസർച്ച് സെന്റർ ഫോർ സിട്രസ്ന്‍റെ ആസ്ഥാനം? ",
    "answerText": " നാഗ്പൂർ "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87413,
    "questionText": " How many words are there in the preamble at present?",
    "answerText": 85
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87414,
    "questionText": " Who drafted the preamble?",
    "answerText": " Jawaharlal Nehru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87415,
    "questionText": " The wording of the preamble of India is close to the preamble to the Constitution of?",
    "answerText": " Ireland"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87416,
    "questionText": " What is referred to as an ‘epitome’ of the broad features of the Constitution?",
    "answerText": " Preamble"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87417,
    "questionText": " The preamble of the Constitution came into force on?",
    "answerText": " 26th January 1950"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87418,
    "questionText": " The preamble of the Constitution begins with?",
    "answerText": " We; the people of India....."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87419,
    "questionText": " Who was the Prime minister of India when the preamble was amended?",
    "answerText": " Indira Gandhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87420,
    "questionText": " How many times the preamble has been amended?",
    "answerText": " Once"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87421,
    "questionText": " The words included in the preamble through the 42nd Amendment?",
    "answerText": " Socialist; Secular; Integrity of nation"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87422,
    "questionText": " The minimum age required to vote in the election to Legislative Assembly?",
    "answerText": 18
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87423,
    "questionText": " Name the Union Territories that have Legislative Assembly?",
    "answerText": " Delhi and Puducherry"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87424,
    "questionText": " Ministers of the State are collectively responsible to the?",
    "answerText": " State Legislative Assembly"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87425,
    "questionText": " The minimum age required to become a candidate for the post of President?",
    "answerText": 35
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87426,
    "questionText": " Who administers the oath of office of the President?",
    "answerText": " Chief Justice of India"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87427,
    "questionText": " If the post of president is vacant, a new president will be elected within ..... months?",
    "answerText": 6
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87428,
    "questionText": " The tenure of the president of India is ...... years.?",
    "answerText": 5
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87429,
    "questionText": " The status of Delhi as per the Constitution?",
    "answerText": " National Capital Territory"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87430,
    "questionText": " Which state has the largest number of Rajya Sabha seats?",
    "answerText": " Uttar Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87431,
    "questionText": " The only Indian state that has its own constitution?",
    "answerText": " Jammu & Kashmir"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87432,
    "questionText": " Which Article of the Constitution deals with special provisions regarding Jammu and Kashmir?",
    "answerText": " 370\\"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87433,
    "questionText": " Which state has the largest number of Lok Sabha seats?",
    "answerText": " U.P."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87434,
    "questionText": " Legislative Assembly of which state has the tenure of six years?",
    "answerText": " Jammu & Kashmir"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87435,
    "questionText": " As per the provisions of the Constitution the minimum strength of State Legislative Assembly is?",
    "answerText": 60
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87436,
    "questionText": " The South Indian states with Legislative Council?",
    "answerText": " Karnataka ;Andhra Pradesh and Telengana"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87437,
    "questionText": " The tenure of member of Legislative Assembly is ...... years?",
    "answerText": " Five"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87438,
    "questionText": " Which State/ Union Territory has the least number of members in its Legislative Assembly?",
    "answerText": " Puducherry"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87439,
    "questionText": " The minimum age required to contest in the election to Legislative Assembly?",
    "answerText": 25
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87440,
    "questionText": " As per the provisions of the Constitution, the strength of State Legislative Assembly is limited upto?",
    "answerText": 500
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87441,
    "questionText": " The Indian state where President’s rule was imposed for the first time?",
    "answerText": " Punjab"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87442,
    "questionText": " Which state has the largest number of Legislative Council seats?",
    "answerText": " Uttar Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87443,
    "questionText": " Which state has the least number of members in its Legislative Assembly?",
    "answerText": " Sikkim"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87444,
    "questionText": " Which state has the least number of Legislative Council seats?",
    "answerText": " Jammu & Kashmir"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87445,
    "questionText": " Which state has the largest number of Legislative Assembly seats?",
    "answerText": " Uttar Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87446,
    "questionText": " The Indian state where Article 356 of the Constitution was imposed for the first time?",
    "answerText": " Kerala"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87447,
    "questionText": " The Article that was related to Right to Property?",
    "answerText": 31
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87448,
    "questionText": " The first country in the world to include Directive Principles in its Constitution?",
    "answerText": " Spanish Republic"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87449,
    "questionText": " The Fundamental Rights in the Indian Constitution have similarity with the Bill of Rights in the Constitution of?",
    "answerText": " USA"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87450,
    "questionText": " The number of Articles related to Fundamental Rights when the original constitution was brought into force?",
    "answerText": 24
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87451,
    "questionText": " The number of Articles when the original constitution was brought into force?",
    "answerText": 395
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87452,
    "questionText": " The Untouchability Offences Act was passed by the Parliament in?",
    "answerText": 1955
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87453,
    "questionText": " During the partition of the country, the provinces that were divided between India and Pakistan were?",
    "answerText": " Punjab and Bengal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87454,
    "questionText": " Fundamental Rights are suspended during?",
    "answerText": " Emergency"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87455,
    "questionText": " If a notice for special session of Lok Sabha was given in writing signed by not less than one-tenth of the members, the president must summon the session within ..... days?",
    "answerText": 14
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87456,
    "questionText": " The Twelfth Schedule was added to the Constitution was added by...... Amendment?",
    "answerText": " 74th"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87457,
    "questionText": " Which amendment of the Constitution empowered the Parliament to amend any part of the Constitution including preamble?",
    "answerText": 24
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87458,
    "questionText": " Which Amendment provided for an authoritative text of the Constitution in Hindi?",
    "answerText": " 58th"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87459,
    "questionText": " Censure motion in Parliament should be supported by atleast ...... members?",
    "answerText": 50
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87460,
    "questionText": " Full statehood was granted to Arunachal Pradesh by .....amendment?",
    "answerText": 55
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87461,
    "questionText": " The Article of the Constitution related to the pardoning power of the President?",
    "answerText": 72
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87462,
    "questionText": " The maximum number of members in the Subordinate Legislation Committee?",
    "answerText": 15
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87463,
    "questionText": " The minimum age prescribed to become the Vice President of India?",
    "answerText": 35
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87464,
    "questionText": " The most powerful upper house of the Legislature in the world?",
    "answerText": " American Senate"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87465,
    "questionText": " The number of members from Lok Sabha to the Public Accounts Committee?",
    "answerText": 7
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87466,
    "questionText": " The number of members from Rajya Sabha to the Public Accounts Committee?",
    "answerText": 15
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87467,
    "questionText": " ‘Right to equal opportunity for justice and free legal aid was added to Directive Principles through ..... amendment?",
    "answerText": 42
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87468,
    "questionText": " The 73rd Amendment of the Constitution was passed by both houses of Parliament in?",
    "answerText": 1992
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87469,
    "questionText": " The 84th amendment of the Constitution in 2000 created ...... states?",
    "answerText": 3
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87470,
    "questionText": " The Amendment that included Bodo, Dogri, Maithili and Santhali in the Eighth Schedule of the Constitution making a total of 22?",
    "answerText": " 92nd"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87471,
    "questionText": " The Amendment that made the right to free and compulsory education a ‘Fundamental Right’?",
    "answerText": " 86th"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87472,
    "questionText": " The Constitutional amendment granted a position of primacy to all Directive Principles over Fundamental Rights?",
    "answerText": 42
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87473,
    "questionText": " The Schedule of the Constitution that was added by 73rd Amendment?",
    "answerText": 11
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87474,
    "questionText": " The number of members in the estimate committee of Parliament?",
    "answerText": 30
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87475,
    "questionText": " The number of members in the Previlege Committee of Parliament?",
    "answerText": 15
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87476,
    "questionText": " The number of members in the Public Accounts Committee of Parliament?",
    "answerText": 30
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87477,
    "questionText": " Which Commonwealth country has the most powerful upper house?",
    "answerText": " Canada"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87478,
    "questionText": " Who elects the deputy chairman of Rajya Sabha?",
    "answerText": " All the members of Rajya Sabha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87479,
    "questionText": " Who is the authority to grant permission to a member of Lok Sabha to speak in his mother tongue if he does not know English or Hindi?",
    "answerText": " Speaker"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87480,
    "questionText": " The number of Articles under the Directive Principles when the Constitution was brought into force?",
    "answerText": 16
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87481,
    "questionText": " On which date Lok Sabha was formed?",
    "answerText": " 17th April; 1952"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87482,
    "questionText": " Maintenance of Internal Security Act (MISA) was passed by the Parliament in?",
    "answerText": 1971
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87483,
    "questionText": " National Security Act (NSA) was passed by the Parliament in?",
    "answerText": 1980
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87484,
    "questionText": " Prevention of Terrorism Act (POTA) was passed by the Parliament in?",
    "answerText": 2002
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87485,
    "questionText": " In the case of resignation, a member of Lok Sabha must submit his resignation to?",
    "answerText": " Speaker"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87486,
    "questionText": " In which kind of emergency can the salaries of even Supreme Court Judges be reduced?",
    "answerText": " Financial"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87487,
    "questionText": " Number of Part A states in India when the Constitution was brought into force?",
    "answerText": 9
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87488,
    "questionText": " The date of first sitting of the first Rajya Sabha?",
    "answerText": " 13-May-52"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87489,
    "questionText": " The first elected president of the Central Legislative Assembly?",
    "answerText": " Vithalbhai Patel"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87490,
    "questionText": " The first speaker of Lok Sabha?",
    "answerText": " GV Mavlankar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87491,
    "questionText": " The most populated princely state at the time of independence?",
    "answerText": " Hyderabad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87492,
    "questionText": " When a proclamation of national emergency is in force, the term of Lok Sabha can be extended by Parliament for the first time for a period not exceeding ...... at a time?",
    "answerText": " One year"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87493,
    "questionText": " Who determines whether a bill is money bill?",
    "answerText": " Speaker"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87494,
    "questionText": " Who was known as ‘father of Lok Sabha’?",
    "answerText": " GV Mavlankar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87495,
    "questionText": " The interval between two consecutive sessions of Lok Sabha shall be less than ........ months?",
    "answerText": 6
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87496,
    "questionText": " Which Article of the Constitution is related to President’s rule in State?",
    "answerText": 356
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87497,
    "questionText": " Union Territory in South India to have Legislative Assembly?",
    "answerText": " Puducherry"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87498,
    "questionText": " The tenure of the president of India is ...... years?",
    "answerText": 5
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87499,
    "questionText": " Supreme Commander of Armed Forces of India?",
    "answerText": " President of India"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87500,
    "questionText": " In case of resignation, the President submits his resignation letter to?",
    "answerText": " Vice President"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87501,
    "questionText": " The procedure for removing the President of India, if he violates the Constitution?",
    "answerText": " Impeachment"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87502,
    "questionText": " The official residence of the President of India, Rashrapathi Bhavan, was designed by?",
    "answerText": " Edwin Lutyens"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87503,
    "questionText": " The position of the President of India is similar to?",
    "answerText": " British Monarch"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87504,
    "questionText": " The idea of elected president as the head of the state has been copied from?",
    "answerText": " Ireland"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87505,
    "questionText": " Constitutional head of the state in India?",
    "answerText": " The President of India"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87506,
    "questionText": " The executive powers of the union of India is vested with?",
    "answerText": " President"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87507,
    "questionText": " Which Article of the Constitution related to impeachment of President?",
    "answerText": 61
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87508,
    "questionText": " Who performs the duties of the President in his/her absense?",
    "answerText": " Vice President"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87509,
    "questionText": " Who performs the duties of the President in his/her absense of Presidend and Vice President?",
    "answerText": " Chief Justice"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87510,
    "questionText": " President is empowered to declare how many types of emergency?",
    "answerText": 3
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87511,
    "questionText": " The ordinances issued by the President must be approved by the President within ...... weeks of the reassembly of Parliament?",
    "answerText": 6
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87512,
    "questionText": " Which Article of the Constitution related to issuance of ordinances by the President?",
    "answerText": 123
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87513,
    "questionText": " From which community the President of India can nominate two members to Lok Sabha to ensure representation?",
    "answerText": " AngloIndian"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87514,
    "questionText": " Who summons the Lok Sabha?",
    "answerText": " President"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87515,
    "questionText": " A person who enjoys all the powers vested in him by the Constitution isc called?",
    "answerText": " Titular sovereign"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87516,
    "questionText": " Who has the power to dissolve the Lok Sabha?",
    "answerText": " The President"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87517,
    "questionText": " The President of India to exercise pocket veto?",
    "answerText": " Zail Singh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87518,
    "questionText": " The Inter-State Council is presided over by?",
    "answerText": " Prime Minister"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87519,
    "questionText": " Who is called ‘the link between the President and the cabinet’?",
    "answerText": " Prime minister"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87520,
    "questionText": " Who is the ex-officio chairman of the Planning Commission?",
    "answerText": " Prime Minister"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87521,
    "questionText": " Who is known as the ‘key stone of the cabinet arch?",
    "answerText": " Prime Minister"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87522,
    "questionText": " Who is called “the first among the equals”?",
    "answerText": " Prime Minister"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87523,
    "questionText": " India borrowed the idea of Fundamental Rights from the Constitutuion of?",
    "answerText": " USA"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87524,
    "questionText": " In which year the Indian National Congress passed a resolution in Madras which declared that ‘the basis of future Constitution of India must be a declaration of Fundamental Rights’?",
    "answerText": 1927
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87525,
    "questionText": " Which session of the Indian National Congress adopted a resolution on Fundamental Rights and Economic and Social Change?",
    "answerText": 1931
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87526,
    "questionText": " In which part of the Constitution the Fundamental Rights are included?",
    "answerText": " III"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87527,
    "questionText": " Who described Part III of Constitution dealing Fundamental Rights as the most criticized part of the Constitution?",
    "answerText": " BR Ambedkar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87528,
    "questionText": " The number of Fundamental Rights when the Constitution was brought into force?",
    "answerText": 7
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87529,
    "questionText": " The number of Fundamental Rights at present?",
    "answerText": 6
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87530,
    "questionText": " Which amendment of the Constitution removed ‘the right to property’ from the list of Fundamental Rights?",
    "answerText": 44
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87531,
    "questionText": " In which year 44th amendment of the Constitution was passed?",
    "answerText": 1978
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87532,
    "questionText": " Who was the prime minister of India when Right to property was deleted from the list of Fundamental Rights?",
    "answerText": " Morarji Desai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87533,
    "questionText": " The Articles of the Constitution of India dealing with Right to Equality?",
    "answerText": " 14 to 18"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87534,
    "questionText": " The Article that deals about Equality before law?",
    "answerText": 14
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87535,
    "questionText": " Which Article of the Constitution is related to prohibition of discrimination on the grounds of religion, race, caste, sex or place of birth?",
    "answerText": 15
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87536,
    "questionText": " Which Article of the Constitution is related to ‘Equality of opportunity in matters of public employment’?",
    "answerText": 16
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87537,
    "questionText": " Which Article of the Constitution is related to ‘Abolition of untouchability’?",
    "answerText": 17
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87538,
    "questionText": " Which Article of the Constitution is related to ‘Abolition of titles’?",
    "answerText": 18
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87539,
    "questionText": " Which Article of the Constitution is related to the protection of certain rights regarding freedom of speech?",
    "answerText": 19
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87540,
    "questionText": " Which Article of the Constitution is related to ‘Protection in respect of convict of offenders’?",
    "answerText": 20
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87541,
    "questionText": " Which Article of the Constitution is related to ‘Protection of life and personal liberty’?",
    "answerText": 21
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87542,
    "questionText": " Which Article of the Constitution is related to ‘Protection against arrest and detention in certain cases’?",
    "answerText": 22
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87543,
    "questionText": " Which article is related to ‘Freedom of Press’?",
    "answerText": " Article 19(1) (a"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87544,
    "questionText": " Which Article was inserted by the 86th amendment of the Constitution to the list of Fundamental Rights?",
    "answerText": " 21A"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87545,
    "questionText": " The president has the power to suspend the enforcement of any or all the Fundamental Rights during emergency as per Article?",
    "answerText": 359
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87546,
    "questionText": " Which Article enacts that all persons are equally entilted to freedom of conscience and the right freely to profess, practice and propagate religion?",
    "answerText": 25
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87547,
    "questionText": " Which Article is related to the ‘Right to Constitutional Remedies’?",
    "answerText": 32
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87548,
    "questionText": " The Artilcles of the Constitution related to Directive Principles of State Policy?",
    "answerText": " 36 to 51"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87549,
    "questionText": " The makers of the Constitution borrowed the idea of Directive Principles of State Policy from the Constitution of?",
    "answerText": " Ireland"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87550,
    "questionText": " Who described Directive Principles of State Policy as a novel feature of the Constitution of India?",
    "answerText": " BR Ambedkar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87551,
    "questionText": " Which enshrines the principles of a welfare state in India?",
    "answerText": " Directive Principles of State Policy"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87552,
    "questionText": " In which part of the Constitution Directive Principles of State Policy are included?",
    "answerText": " IV"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87553,
    "questionText": " Who compared Directive Principles of State Policy to the Instrument of Instructions in the Govt. of India Act, 1935?",
    "answerText": " BR Ambedkar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87554,
    "questionText": " Which part of the Constitution reflects some Gandhian ideals?",
    "answerText": " Directive Principles of State Policy"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87555,
    "questionText": " The state shall organise village panchayats as units of self government. This is enshrined in Article?",
    "answerText": 40
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87556,
    "questionText": " The state shall promote with special care the educational and economic interests of weaker sections of people. To which Article this is related?",
    "answerText": 45
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87557,
    "questionText": " Which Article states that “State shall try to promote cottage industries”?",
    "answerText": 43
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87558,
    "questionText": " The Article related to the prohibition of cow slaughter?",
    "answerText": 48
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87559,
    "questionText": " Which Article under Directive Principles of State Policy is related to prohibition of indoxicating drinks and drugs?",
    "answerText": 47
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87560,
    "questionText": " Which Article declares that the state shall endeavour to promote international peace and security?",
    "answerText": 51
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87561,
    "questionText": " Which Articles is related to uniform civil code?",
    "answerText": 44
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87562,
    "questionText": " Who described ‘Directive Principles’ as a cheque payable by the bank when able only when the resources of the bank permit?",
    "answerText": " KT Shaw"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87563,
    "questionText": " The only state in India where uniform civil code has been implemented?",
    "answerText": " Goa"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87564,
    "questionText": " Which Article is related to the separation of judiciary from executive?",
    "answerText": 50
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87565,
    "questionText": " Which part of the Constitution was criticised as ‘New year resolutions which were broken on the second January” by M Nasiruddin, one of the members of Constituent Assembly?",
    "answerText": " Directive Principles"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87566,
    "questionText": " Ireland copied Directive Principles from the Constitution of?",
    "answerText": " Spanish Republic"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87567,
    "questionText": " Who made the comment that Directive Principles of State Policy expresses Fabian Socialism without the word ‘Socialism’?",
    "answerText": " Ivor Jennings"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87568,
    "questionText": " From which country India adopted the ideas of Fundamental Duties?",
    "answerText": " Formenr USSR"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87569,
    "questionText": " The number of Fundamental Duties in the Indian Constitution?",
    "answerText": 11
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87570,
    "questionText": " In which Article of the Constitution Fundamental Duties are mentioned?",
    "answerText": 51
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87571,
    "questionText": " Which Article of the Constitution deals with Amendment procedure?",
    "answerText": 368
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87572,
    "questionText": " In how many ways the Constitution of India can be amended?",
    "answerText": 3
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87573,
    "questionText": " Amendment by special majority means the bill is passed in each house by a majority of the total membership and by a majority not less than ........ of the members that house present and voting?",
    "answerText": " Two thirds"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87574,
    "questionText": " Amendment that needs ratification by states must be ratified by Legislatures of not less than ...... of the states?",
    "answerText": " One half"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87575,
    "questionText": " From which country India copied the procedure of amendment of Constitution?",
    "answerText": " South Africa"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87576,
    "questionText": " In which year the first Constitution Bill was passed?",
    "answerText": 1951
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87577,
    "questionText": " Which Schedule of the Constitution was added by the first amendment of the Constitution?",
    "answerText": " Ninth"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87578,
    "questionText": " Which amendment is related to reorganisation of states on linguistic basis (1956)?",
    "answerText": " 7th"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87579,
    "questionText": " Which amendment of the Constitution gave Assosiated State status to Sikkim?",
    "answerText": " 35th"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87580,
    "questionText": " The largest amendment of the Constitution was?",
    "answerText": " 42nd"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87581,
    "questionText": " The 42nd Amendment was introduced after the recommendations of ..... Committee?",
    "answerText": " Swaran Singh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87582,
    "questionText": " Which Amendment of the Constitution changed its charecterisation from ‘Soverign Democratic Republic’ to ‘Sovereign Socialist Secular Democratic Republic’?",
    "answerText": " 42nd"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87583,
    "questionText": " By which Amendment the words in the preamble of the Constitution- ‘Unity of nation’ were changed to ‘Unity and Integrity of Nation’?",
    "answerText": " 42nd"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87584,
    "questionText": " By which amendent the life of Lok Sabha and State Assemblies was extended from 5 to 6 years?",
    "answerText": " 42nd"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87585,
    "questionText": " Fundamental Duties were included in the Constitution through which amendment of Constitution?",
    "answerText": " 42nd Amendment?"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87586,
    "questionText": " The Amendment of the Constitution that restored the life of Lok Sabha and State Assemblies from 6 years to five years?",
    "answerText": " 44th"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87587,
    "questionText": " Which Amendement is related to AntiDefection Law?",
    "answerText": " 52nd"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87588,
    "questionText": " Renaissance in Kerala",
    "answerText": " X"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87589,
    "questionText": " The founder of ‘Samathwa Samajam”?",
    "answerText": " Ayya Vaikundar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87590,
    "questionText": " The founder of ‘Travancore Ezhava Sabha’?",
    "answerText": " Dr.Palpu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87591,
    "questionText": " Sree Narayana Guru visited the Satyagrahis at Vaikkom in?",
    "answerText": 1924
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87592,
    "questionText": " The Maharaja of Travancore who invited Thycaud Ayya to his palace and became his disciple?",
    "answerText": " Swati Tirunal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87593,
    "questionText": " One of the leaders of Kerala renaissanmce who served as the manager of Residency in Thiruvananthapuram?",
    "answerText": " Thycaud Ayya"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87594,
    "questionText": " Panmana Ashramam is related to?",
    "answerText": " Chattampi Swamikal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87595,
    "questionText": " Prabodha Chandrodayam Sabha patronised by Pandit Karuppan had its seat at?",
    "answerText": " North Paravur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87596,
    "questionText": " Sahodaran Ayyappan launched ‘Mishrabhojanam’ programme at Cherayi in?",
    "answerText": 1917
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87597,
    "questionText": " Sivagiri Theerthadanam, was conceived by Vallabhasseri Govindan Vaidyar and _____?",
    "answerText": " T K Kittan Writer"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87598,
    "questionText": " Who was instrumental in the establishment of “Muslim Aikya Sangham”, a united Muslim forum for all the Muslims of the Travancore, Cochin and Malabar regions?",
    "answerText": " Vakkom Maulavi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87599,
    "questionText": " Who was also known as ‘Kumara Gurudevan’?",
    "answerText": " Poikayil Yohannan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87600,
    "questionText": " Who was also known by the name ‘Sree Bhatarakan’?",
    "answerText": " Chattampi Swamikal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87601,
    "questionText": " Who was born in 1814 in Nakalapuram?",
    "answerText": " Thycaud Ayya"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87602,
    "questionText": " Who was called the ‘Lincoln of Kerala’?",
    "answerText": " Pandit Karuppan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87603,
    "questionText": " Sree Narayana Dharma Sangham was registed in?",
    "answerText": 1928
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87604,
    "questionText": " Sree Narayana Guru made his first visit to Sri Lanka in?",
    "answerText": 1918
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87605,
    "questionText": " The founder of All Travancore Muslim Mahajanasabha?",
    "answerText": " Vakkom Moulavi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87606,
    "questionText": " Kumaranasan passed away in?",
    "answerText": 1924
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87607,
    "questionText": " Kumaranasan was born in the year?",
    "answerText": 1873
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87608,
    "questionText": " Kummampalli Raman pillai Asan was the teacher of?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87609,
    "questionText": " Name the organisation jointly launched by Mannath Padmanabhan and R.Sankar?",
    "answerText": " Hindu Maha Mandalam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87610,
    "questionText": " Name the social reformer who had contacts with Sree Narayana Guru and Brahmananda Sivayogi?",
    "answerText": " Vagbhatananda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87611,
    "questionText": " Name the social reformer whose education was started after attaining the age of 17?",
    "answerText": " V.T.Bhatathirippad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87612,
    "questionText": " The founder of Ananda Maha Sabha?",
    "answerText": " Brahmananda Swami Sivayogi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87613,
    "questionText": " Who founded ‘Vidhyaposhini’, a cultural organisation?",
    "answerText": " Sahodaran Ayyappan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87614,
    "questionText": " Who founded Prathyaksha Raksha Daiva Sabha?",
    "answerText": " Poikayil Yohannan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87615,
    "questionText": " Who started the publication of a journal called ‘Abhinava Kerala’?",
    "answerText": " Vagbhatananda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87616,
    "questionText": " Who studied at the ‘Patasala’ of Pettayil Raman Pillai asan and became the monitor of the class?",
    "answerText": " Chattampi Swamikal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87617,
    "questionText": " Who translated the ‘Atmopadeshasatakam’ of Sree Narayana Guru into English with the Title ‘Centiloquy to the Self”?",
    "answerText": " Nataraja Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87618,
    "questionText": " Who translated the dialogue between Tagore and Narayana Guru into Malayalam during Tagore’s visit to Sivagiri?",
    "answerText": " Kumaranasan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87619,
    "questionText": " The name ‘Muthukutty’ was the childhood name of?",
    "answerText": " Ayya Vaikundar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87620,
    "questionText": " The first to establish a printing press in Kerala without foreign support?",
    "answerText": " Kuriakode Elias Chavara"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87621,
    "questionText": " The founder of ‘Islam Dharma Paripalana Sangham’?",
    "answerText": " Vakkom Moulavi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87622,
    "questionText": " “Ask not, Say not, think not caste” are the words of?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87623,
    "questionText": " ‘Adwaitha Chintha Paddhathi was written by’?",
    "answerText": " Chattampi Swamikal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87624,
    "questionText": " ‘Baalaakalesam’ was autored by?",
    "answerText": " Pandit Karuppan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87625,
    "questionText": " ‘Daiva Dasakam’ was authored by?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87626,
    "questionText": " “His grandfather Hrishikesan and his father Muthukumaran were great yogis and were migrated to Tamilnadu from Pampumkadu in Malabar during Tipu Sultan’s aggression. Lord Subramanya was their family deity. At the age of 12, he received spiritual initiation from two Tamil Saints, Sachidananda Maharaj and Sri Chitti Paradeshi.”-The person mentioned here is?",
    "answerText": " Thycaud Ayya"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87627,
    "questionText": " “I consider it the greatest good fortune of my life to have visited the beautiful Travancore state and met the most venerable saint, Sree Narayana Guru Swami trippadangal” Who wrote these words in the guest book at Sivagiri?",
    "answerText": " - Gandhiji"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87628,
    "questionText": " The leaders of renaissance who were born in 1863?",
    "answerText": " Ayyankali and Dr.Palpu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87629,
    "questionText": " The Malayalam poet who had prominent Buddhist influence in his writings?",
    "answerText": " Kumaranasan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87630,
    "questionText": " The mouth piece of Sadhujana Paripalana Sangham, started in 1913?",
    "answerText": " Sadhujana Paripalini"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87631,
    "questionText": " The Ezhava Memorial of 1900 was submitted before?",
    "answerText": " Lord Curzon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87632,
    "questionText": " The first European disciple of Sree Narayana Guru?",
    "answerText": " Ernest Kirk"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87633,
    "questionText": " The first medical graduate from Ezhava community in Travancore?",
    "answerText": " Dr.Palpu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87634,
    "questionText": " Acts that one performs For one’s own sake Should also aim for the good Of other menare the words of?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87635,
    "questionText": " “Without differences of caste,Nor enmities of creed, Here it is, the model of an abode,where all live like brothers at heart” - these words were inscribed by Narayana Guru on a plaque at?",
    "answerText": " Aruvippuram"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87636,
    "questionText": " “The people who form the Ezhava samajam and Nair samajam are themselves proclaiming that they are non-Brahmins and are of backward class, thereby destroying their eminence and unity”-Who said this?",
    "answerText": " Brahmananda Sivayogi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87637,
    "questionText": " “To change the Nampoothiri into human” was the slogan of which organisation?",
    "answerText": " Yogakshema Sabha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87638,
    "questionText": " “Whatever the religion, attire, language and such other things of human kind, as they belong to same caste (species) there is no harm in interdining and intermarriage between them”-Sree Narayana Guru made this suggestion to?",
    "answerText": " Sahodaran Ayyappan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87639,
    "questionText": " In which state is Marutwamala?",
    "answerText": " Tamil Nadu (Kanyakumari district)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87640,
    "questionText": " In which year Dr.P.Palpu was born?",
    "answerText": 1863
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87641,
    "questionText": " In which year Kumaranasan became the president of S.N.D.P.Yogam?",
    "answerText": 1923
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87642,
    "questionText": " In which year Kuriakose Elias Chavara was born?",
    "answerText": 1805
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87643,
    "questionText": " In which year Narayana Guru did the prathishta of the goddess Sree Sarada at Sivagiri?",
    "answerText": " 1912 (April)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87644,
    "questionText": " In which year Sadhujana Paripalana Sangham became ‘Pulaya Mahasabha’?",
    "answerText": 1938
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87645,
    "questionText": " In which year Sree Narayana Guru established Adwaithasramam at Aluva?",
    "answerText": 1914
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87646,
    "questionText": " In which year Thycaud Ayya passed away?",
    "answerText": 1909
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87647,
    "questionText": " “Not for argument but to know and inform others” these words were the theme of the conferece held at____ under the leadership of Sree Narayana Guru in 1924?",
    "answerText": " Aluva"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87648,
    "questionText": " “Organize and strengthen, Educate and Enlighten” are the words of?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87649,
    "questionText": " “Oru jathy, oru matham ,oru Daivom” (“Intha ulakathile orae oru jathy than, Orae oru matham than, orae oru kadavul than” ) is the Malayalam translation of Thycaud Ayya’s teaching . Who popularised it?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87650,
    "questionText": " Dr.Palpu served in the medical service under the government of?",
    "answerText": " Mysore"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87651,
    "questionText": " From where the Begging March of V.T.Bhatathirippad was started?",
    "answerText": " Thrissur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87652,
    "questionText": " ‘I have been touring different parts of the world. During these travels, I have had the good fortune to come into contact with several saints and maharshis. But I have frankly to admit that I have never come across one who is spiritually greater than Swami Sree Narayana Guru of Kerala” Whose words are these?",
    "answerText": " Rabindranath Tagore"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87653,
    "questionText": " In What was the aim of Begging March (Yachana Yatra) organised by V.T.Bhatathirippad?",
    "answerText": " - to provide opportunity of education for poor children"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87654,
    "questionText": " In which district was the Perinad strike held?",
    "answerText": " Kollam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87655,
    "questionText": " Moksha Pradeepa Khandanam was written by?",
    "answerText": " Chattampi Swamikal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87656,
    "questionText": " Name the leader of renaissance who became a minister in Travancore Cochin?",
    "answerText": " Sahodaran Ayyappan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87657,
    "questionText": " Who was honoured by the Maharaja of Cochin with the title ‘Kavithilakan’?",
    "answerText": " Pandit Karuppan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87658,
    "questionText": " Who was known as the ‘Saint without Saffron’?",
    "answerText": " Chattampi Swamikal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87659,
    "questionText": " Who was named Komaran at his birth?",
    "answerText": " Poikayil Yohannan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87660,
    "questionText": " Who was respectfully called “Superintend Ayya”?",
    "answerText": " Thycaud Ayya"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87661,
    "questionText": " Who was the Chief Minister when the Government of Kerala decided to return the press that had been confiscated in 1910 to the descendants of Vakkom Maulavi, in 1957?",
    "answerText": " E.M.S.Namboothirippad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87662,
    "questionText": " Who was the first to introduc the system called “A school along with every church”?",
    "answerText": " Kuriakose Elias Chavara"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87663,
    "questionText": " Name the leader of renaissance who was ousted from his caste for the reason of attending the Ahmedabad Congress Session of 1921?",
    "answerText": " V.T.Bhatatirippad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87664,
    "questionText": " Name the leader related to the ‘Muthukulam Speech’ of 1947?",
    "answerText": " Mannath Padmanabhan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87665,
    "questionText": " Name the leaders of renaissance of Kerala who kept a warm relationship throughout their life from the beginnig of their friendship?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru and Chattampi Swamikal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87666,
    "questionText": " Name the newspaper started by C.V.Kunhuraman in 1911 to propagate the ideals of Sree Narayana Guru?",
    "answerText": " Kerala Kaumudi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87667,
    "questionText": " In which year was the Begging March of V.T.Bhatathirippad?",
    "answerText": 1931
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87668,
    "questionText": " Jaathikkummi is the famous work of?",
    "answerText": " Pandit Karuppan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87669,
    "questionText": " Jnanodayam Sabha’ was founded under the patronage of Pandit Karuppan at?",
    "answerText": " Edakochi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87670,
    "questionText": " Kumarakodi is the final resting place of?",
    "answerText": " Kumaranasan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87671,
    "questionText": " The birth place of Mannath Padmanabhan?",
    "answerText": " Perunna"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87672,
    "questionText": " The elegy ‘Prarodanam’ mourns the death of his contemporary and friend ______?",
    "answerText": " A. R. Raja Raja Varma"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87673,
    "questionText": " The founder of Thathva Prakashika Ashram at Kozhikode?",
    "answerText": " Vagbhatananda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87674,
    "questionText": " The Goverment of Travancore issued orders to open the approach roads to temples to all avarnas in the year?",
    "answerText": 1928
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87675,
    "questionText": " Nirvritipachakam was written by?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87676,
    "questionText": " The first member of Pulaya community to be nominated to Travancore Legislative Assembly?",
    "answerText": " Ayyankali"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87677,
    "questionText": " The first Sanyasa disciple of Sree Narayana Guru?",
    "answerText": " Sivalinga Swamikal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87678,
    "questionText": " The organiser of ‘Kalyanadayini Sabha’?",
    "answerText": " Pandit Karuppan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87679,
    "questionText": " The original name of Thycaud Ayya was?",
    "answerText": " Subbarayan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87680,
    "questionText": " The Perinad strike was led by?",
    "answerText": " Ayyankali"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87681,
    "questionText": " The personality who was visited by Narayana Guru at Thiruvannamala, Tamil nadu in 1916?",
    "answerText": " Ramana Maharshi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87682,
    "questionText": " The place selected by Narayana Guru when he decided to give up his wandering life and settle down?",
    "answerText": " Varkala"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87683,
    "questionText": " The place where Ayyankali started a ‘Kudippallikkoodam’ for the depressed classes in 1905?",
    "answerText": " Venganur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87684,
    "questionText": " The place where Ayyankali started a school for the depressed classes in 1904?",
    "answerText": " Venganur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87685,
    "questionText": " The place where Dr.Palpu was born?",
    "answerText": " Pettah"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87686,
    "questionText": " Who called Kumaranasan as ‘Chinna Swami’?",
    "answerText": " Dr.Palpu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87687,
    "questionText": " Who called the rule of English as ‘White Devil’ and the rule of the King of Travancore as the ‘Devil of Ananthapuri’?",
    "answerText": " Ayya Vaikundar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87688,
    "questionText": " Who conferred the Title of ‘Vidwan’ upon Pandit Karuppan in 1913?",
    "answerText": " Keralavarma Valiakoithampuran of Travancore"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87689,
    "questionText": " Narayana Guru’s second visit to Sri Lanka was in?",
    "answerText": 1926
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87690,
    "questionText": " Neelakanda Theerthapadar was the disciple of?",
    "answerText": " Chattampi Swamikal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87691,
    "questionText": " The place where Narayana guru is believed to have attained a state of Enlightenment?",
    "answerText": " Maruthwamala"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87692,
    "questionText": " The real name of Brahmananda Sivayogi?",
    "answerText": " Karat Govindankutty Menon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87693,
    "questionText": " Who ousted god from the centre and placed mind in its place?",
    "answerText": " Brahmananda Sivayogi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87694,
    "questionText": " Who passed away on the previous day of India becoming a republic?",
    "answerText": " Dr.Palpu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87695,
    "questionText": " Who patronised ‘Sudharma Sooryodaya Sabha’ at Thevara?",
    "answerText": " Pandit Karuppan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87696,
    "questionText": " The real name of Vagbhatananda Gurudevar?",
    "answerText": " V.K.Gurukkal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87697,
    "questionText": " Vakkom Abdul Khadir Moulaviwas born in 1873 in _____ district?",
    "answerText": " Thiruvananthapuram"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87698,
    "questionText": " Vakkom Maulavi passed away in?",
    "answerText": 1932
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87699,
    "questionText": " Vedadhikara Niroopanam was authored by?",
    "answerText": " Chattampi Swamikal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87700,
    "questionText": " The birth place of Chattampi Swamikal?",
    "answerText": " - Kollur (Kannammula)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87701,
    "questionText": " What was the pet name of Chattampi Swamikal?",
    "answerText": " Kunjan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87702,
    "questionText": " The social reformer who inspired the formation of ‘Karshaka Sangham’ in Malabar?",
    "answerText": " Vagbhatananda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87703,
    "questionText": " The social reformer who said “Mind is God”?",
    "answerText": " Brahmananda Sivayogi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87704,
    "questionText": " The third signatory in the Malayali Memorial (1891) a mass petition signed by more than 10000 persons submitted before Sree Mulam Tirunal, the King of Travancore?",
    "answerText": " Dr.Palpu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87705,
    "questionText": " The Visit of Mahathma Gandhi at Vaikom Satyagraha in the year?",
    "answerText": 1925
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87706,
    "questionText": " Who advised Dr. Palpu to associate with some spiritual person in his effort to fight for the rights of the Ezhavas?",
    "answerText": " Vivekananda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87707,
    "questionText": " Who advised the organisers of Vaikom Satyagraha to conduct ‘Savarna Jatha’?",
    "answerText": " Mahathma Gandhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87708,
    "questionText": " The birth place of Vaikunta Swamikal?",
    "answerText": " Swamithoppe"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87709,
    "questionText": " Which agitation is also known as “Thonnooramand Lahala’?",
    "answerText": " Oorutapalam revolt"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87710,
    "questionText": " Which organisation inspired Ayyan Kali to establish Sadhujana Paripalana Sangham?",
    "answerText": " SNDP Yogam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87711,
    "questionText": " Who authored ‘Mokshapradeepam’?",
    "answerText": " Brahmananada Sivayogi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87712,
    "questionText": " The remains of Chavara Kuriakose Alias is kept at?",
    "answerText": " Mannanam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87713,
    "questionText": " Who called Kumaranasan “the Poet of Renaissance’?",
    "answerText": " Thayatt Sankaran"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87714,
    "questionText": " Who authored ‘Anandasutram’?",
    "answerText": " Brahmananada Sivayogi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87715,
    "questionText": " Who authored ‘Divyakokilam’ as a tribute to Rabindranath Tagore?",
    "answerText": " Kumaranasan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87716,
    "questionText": " The work of Kumaranasan that depicts the fact ‘Mamsanibhadamalla ragam’ (Love is not an artifact of flesh)?",
    "answerText": " Leela"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87717,
    "questionText": " The work of Kumaransan on the background of the Malabar Rebellion of 1921?",
    "answerText": " Duravastha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87718,
    "questionText": " The world rises from love /And attains progress with love,/Love is itself the power of the world,/Love brings happiness to all; / Love is life itself, sir,/And Love’s absence is death”-The work of Kumaranasan which depicts the sacredness of love?",
    "answerText": " Chandalabhikshuki"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87719,
    "questionText": " The year of Liberation Struggle?",
    "answerText": 1959
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87720,
    "questionText": " The year of Perinad Revolt led by Ayyankali?",
    "answerText": 1915
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87721,
    "questionText": " Who founded the Siddhasramam at Alathur?",
    "answerText": " Brahmananda Swami Sivayogi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87722,
    "questionText": " Who gave a detailed explanation of ‘Chinmudra’ to Swami Vivekananda when he visited Kerala?",
    "answerText": " Chattampi Swamikal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87723,
    "questionText": " Who gave financial aid to Kumaranasan to get education from Bangalore and Kolkata?",
    "answerText": " Dr.Palpu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87724,
    "questionText": " Who headed a deputation which submitted a memoradum signed by 23000 persons before the Regent Queen during the Vaikom Satyagraha?",
    "answerText": " Changanassery Parameswaran Pillai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87725,
    "questionText": " Who introduced Thycaud Ayya to Sree Narayana Guru?",
    "answerText": " Chattampi Swamikal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87726,
    "questionText": " Who expounded the concept of ‘Aananthajathi’?",
    "answerText": " Brahmananda Sivayogi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87727,
    "questionText": " Who expounded the philosophy “Snehamanakhilasaramoozhiyil” (Love is all in this world) in his writings?",
    "answerText": " Kumaranasan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87728,
    "questionText": " Who undertook a studentship in poetry under Manamboor Govindan Asan?",
    "answerText": " Kumaranasan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87729,
    "questionText": " Who was declared as his successor by Sree Narayana Guru in 1925?",
    "answerText": " Bodhananda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87730,
    "questionText": " Who was given the name ‘Mudichoodum Perumal’ by his parents?",
    "answerText": " Ayya Vaikundar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87731,
    "questionText": " Who was the only person who was exempted from court appearances in civil cases by Government of Travancore?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87732,
    "questionText": " Who wrote Darshanamala?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87733,
    "questionText": " Who wrote introduction to ‘Nalini’ written by Kumaranasan?",
    "answerText": " A.R.Rajaraja Varma"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87734,
    "questionText": " Who, on the basis of logical reasoning rejected all existing religions and at the same time established a new religion called ‘Aananthamath’?",
    "answerText": " Brahmananda Sivayogi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87735,
    "questionText": " Whom Sardar K.M.Panicker called the ‘Madan Mohan Malavya of Kerala’?",
    "answerText": " Mannath Padmanabhan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87736,
    "questionText": " Whose childhood name was ‘Kumaru’?",
    "answerText": " Kumaranasan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87737,
    "questionText": " The headquarters of Prathyaksha Raksha Daiva Sabha?",
    "answerText": " Eraviperoor"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87738,
    "questionText": " The last Sanyasa disciple of Sree Narayana Guru?",
    "answerText": " Anandatheertha Swamikal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87739,
    "questionText": " The author of ‘Adukkalayilninnu Arangathekku’?",
    "answerText": " V.T.Bhatathirippad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87740,
    "questionText": " Cochin Pulaya Maha Sabha was founded by?",
    "answerText": " Pandit Karuppan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87741,
    "questionText": " Who organised interdining at Kozhikode and called it “Preethibhojanam”?",
    "answerText": " Vagbhatananda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87742,
    "questionText": " Who presided over the All Communities Conference organised by Ayyankali on 10th December 1915 in connection with the Perinad strike?",
    "answerText": " Changanassery Parameswaran Pillai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87743,
    "questionText": " Who raised the concept of ‘Dravida dalit’ who is neither Hindu nor Christian?",
    "answerText": " Kumaragurudevan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87744,
    "questionText": " Who said “No caste, no religion, no god for man”?",
    "answerText": " Sahodaran Ayyappan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87745,
    "questionText": " Who said these words “I installed my siva; not a Brahmin siva”?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87746,
    "questionText": " Who started the publication ‘Saragrahi’ to propagate his ideals?",
    "answerText": " Brahmananda Sivayogi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87747,
    "questionText": " After becoming the disciple of Sree Narayana Guru to which place Kumaru (Kumaranasan) was sent for higher studies in Sanskrit?",
    "answerText": " Bangalore"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87748,
    "questionText": " Who is regarded as the father of the renaissance of Kerala?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87749,
    "questionText": " Who led the first organised strike of agricultural labourers in Travancore?",
    "answerText": " Ayyankali"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87750,
    "questionText": " Aggrieved by the death of Sree Chattambi Swamikal, who wrote a condolence poem namely ‘Samadhi Sapthakam’?",
    "answerText": " Pandit Karuppan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87751,
    "questionText": " Al-Islam , The Muslim and Deepika were published by?",
    "answerText": " Vakkom Moulavi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87752,
    "questionText": " Araya Vamsodharani Sabha had its seat at?",
    "answerText": " Engandiyoor"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87753,
    "questionText": " Atmopadeshasatakam was authored by?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87754,
    "questionText": " Ayyankali passed away in?",
    "answerText": 1941
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87755,
    "questionText": " Bodheswaran, Perunnelli Krishnan Vaidhyan, Velutheri Kesavan Vaidhyan, Kumbalath Sanku Pillai etc were grihastha disciples of?",
    "answerText": " Chattampi Swamikal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87756,
    "questionText": " Brahmananda Swami Sivayogi was born in?",
    "answerText": 1852
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87757,
    "questionText": " The place which was selected by Nanu Asan (Narayana Guru) as his abode for meditation and spiritual activities?",
    "answerText": " Aruvippuram"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87758,
    "questionText": " The prefix ‘Mahakavi’ awarded to Kumaranasan by Madras University in the year ___?",
    "answerText": 1922
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87759,
    "questionText": " The presiding deity of the Thycaud Ayya Swami Temple?",
    "answerText": " Shiva"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87760,
    "questionText": " The name ‘Sivagiri’ was given to the mount at Varkala by?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87761,
    "questionText": " The name ‘Vagbhatananda’ was given to V.K.Gurukkal by?",
    "answerText": " Sivayogi of Alathur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87762,
    "questionText": " The name of the boat Kumaranasan was travelling before he met an accident that caused his death?",
    "answerText": " Redeemer"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87763,
    "questionText": " The novel ‘Guru’ depicts the life of Sree Narayana Guru is authored by?",
    "answerText": " K.Surendran"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87764,
    "questionText": " Who is called the father of literacy in Kerala?",
    "answerText": " Kuriakose Elias Chavara"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87765,
    "questionText": " Who called Kumaranasan ‘Viplavathinte Sukranakshatram’?",
    "answerText": " Joseph Mundassery"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87766,
    "questionText": " Who exhorted ‘Mattuvin Chattangele’ (Change the rules)?",
    "answerText": " Kumaranasan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87767,
    "questionText": " The only foreign country visited by Sree Narayana Guru?",
    "answerText": " Sri Lanka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87768,
    "questionText": " The only Keralite whose birth day and death anniversary are declared holiday by the Government of Kerala?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87769,
    "questionText": " The publication ‘The Muslim’ was launched by Vakkom Moulavi in?",
    "answerText": 1906
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87770,
    "questionText": " Chattampi Swamikal aquired self realization at?",
    "answerText": " Vadaveeswaram"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87771,
    "questionText": " Who is referred to as the “father of muslim renaissance in Kerala”?",
    "answerText": " Vakkom Moulavi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87772,
    "questionText": " Who led the starvation march?",
    "answerText": " V.T.Bhatatirippad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87773,
    "questionText": " Vagbhatananda Gurudevar was a disciple of?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87774,
    "questionText": " Who became the editor of ‘Yukthivadi’ magazine in 1928?",
    "answerText": " Sahodaran Ayyappan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87775,
    "questionText": " Who became the first president of the Travancore Devaswam Board in 1949?",
    "answerText": " Mannath Padmanabhan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87776,
    "questionText": " Who called Kerala “a lunatic asylum’?",
    "answerText": " Vivekananda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87777,
    "questionText": " ‘Navamanjari’ written by Sree Narayana Guru is dedicated to?",
    "answerText": " Chattampi Swamikal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87778,
    "questionText": " ‘Prachina Malayalam’ was authored by?",
    "answerText": " Chattampi Swamikal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87779,
    "questionText": " “ Whatever may be the religion of a man, it is enough if he becomes virtuous “ are the words of?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87780,
    "questionText": " “ Liquor is poison, make it not, sell it not, drink it not” are the words of?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87781,
    "questionText": " “Freedom alone is nectar divine; Freedom is life itself; To a self-respecting people Slavery is more terrible than death”- Who wrote these lines?",
    "answerText": " Kumaranasan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87782,
    "questionText": " The only poet in Malayalam who became ‘mahakavi’ without writing a ‘mahakavyam’?",
    "answerText": " Kumaranasan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87783,
    "questionText": " Who is regared as the greatest Keralite of 20th century?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87784,
    "questionText": " Who led ‘Kallumala (Stone ornament) Agitation”?",
    "answerText": " Ayyankali"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87785,
    "questionText": " Who led agitation against oozhiyavela (forced labour)?",
    "answerText": " Ayya Vaikunatar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87786,
    "questionText": " The last temple consecrated by Sree Narayana Guru?",
    "answerText": " Kalavankode"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87787,
    "questionText": " The leaders of renaissance who passed away in the same year of 1924?",
    "answerText": " Chattampi Swamikal and Kumaranasan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87788,
    "questionText": " In which year AK Gopalan led ‘starvatiom march’ from Kannur to Madras with 32 followers?",
    "answerText": 1936
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87789,
    "questionText": " In which year an agricultural and industrial fair was organised under the initiative of Sree Narayana Guru at Kollam?",
    "answerText": 1905
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87790,
    "questionText": " In which year Sree Narayana Guru and Kumaranasan met for the first time?",
    "answerText": 1891
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87791,
    "questionText": " The temple where Sree Narayana Guru met Chattampi Swamikal for the first time?",
    "answerText": " Aniyoor"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87792,
    "questionText": " The film ‘Yugapurushan’ depicts the life of?",
    "answerText": " Srinarayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87793,
    "questionText": " Who directed the film ‘Yugapurushan’?",
    "answerText": " R.Sukumaran"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87794,
    "questionText": " The year in which Sree Narayana Guru gave the message ‘One caste, one religion, one god for man’ at a conference held at ‘Adwaithasramam’, Aluva?",
    "answerText": 1924
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87795,
    "questionText": " Rabindranath Tagore visited Sree Narayana Guru at Sivagiri in?",
    "answerText": 1922
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87796,
    "questionText": " Headquarters of Nair Service Society is at?",
    "answerText": " Perunna"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87797,
    "questionText": " Vakkom Maulavi started ‘Swadeshabhimani’ in?",
    "answerText": 1905
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87798,
    "questionText": " Who played a key role along with M Govindan in the publication of Vivekodayam which started publication in 1904 as the mouth piece of the SNDP Yogam?",
    "answerText": " Kumaranasan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87799,
    "questionText": " For the installation of idol in which temple, Sree Narayana Guru reached there with Chattampi Swamikal?",
    "answerText": " Poothotta Sree Vallabheswara Temple"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87800,
    "questionText": " For which community Sree Narayana Guru consecrated Thiruppatheeswara Temple at Mangalore?",
    "answerText": " Billava"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87801,
    "questionText": " The headquarters of SNDP Yogam?",
    "answerText": " Kollam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87802,
    "questionText": " Who was the volunteer captain of Guruvayur Sathyagraha?",
    "answerText": " A.K.Gopalan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87803,
    "questionText": " Who led the ‘Liberation Struggle’?",
    "answerText": " Mannath Padmanabhan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87804,
    "questionText": " Whose ancestral home was ‘Vayalvaram Veedu’?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87805,
    "questionText": " Who took initiative to file a counter memorial in favour of Brahmins, against the Malayali Memorial?",
    "answerText": " Chenkotta Ramayyar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87806,
    "questionText": " Who was the official editor of ‘Vivekodayam’ when it was started in 1904?",
    "answerText": " M.Govindan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87807,
    "questionText": " Yogakshemasabha aimed at the welfare of ____?",
    "answerText": " Brahmins"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87808,
    "questionText": " In which year Yogakshemasabha was founded?",
    "answerText": 1908
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87809,
    "questionText": " Who was a disciple of Kollur Krishna Pillai and Pettayil Raman Pillai Asan?",
    "answerText": " Chattampi Swamikal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87810,
    "questionText": " Whose sisters were Kochu, Thevi and Matha?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87811,
    "questionText": " At which place Sree Narayana Guru installed the idol of Subramanya for the first time?",
    "answerText": " Vakkom"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87812,
    "questionText": " Which temple consecrated by Sree Narayana Guru is also called Velayudhan Nada?",
    "answerText": " Vakkom Subramanya Swami Temple"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87813,
    "questionText": " Kerala Yuktivadi Sangham was established at Thrissur in?",
    "answerText": 1964
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87814,
    "questionText": " Who was the first president of Kerala Yuktivadi Sangham?",
    "answerText": " M.C.Josheph"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87815,
    "questionText": " Which organisation encouraged ‘Misrabhojanam’ to annihilate the evils of caste system?",
    "answerText": " Sahodara Sangham"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87816,
    "questionText": " Who was called ‘Vaikom Veerar?",
    "answerText": " E.V.Ramaswami Naicker"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87817,
    "questionText": " Which Satyagraha was conducted after independence?",
    "answerText": " Paliyam Satyagraha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87818,
    "questionText": " The famous personality of Malabar who embraced Buddhism in 1926?",
    "answerText": " C.Krishnan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87819,
    "questionText": " The slogan ‘Travancore for Travancoreans’ is related to?",
    "answerText": " Malayali Memorial"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87820,
    "questionText": " The date of Temple Entry Proclamation in Travancore?",
    "answerText": " 12 th Novemeber 1936"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87821,
    "questionText": " Brahmananda Swami Sivayogi founded?",
    "answerText": " Ananda Maha Sabha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87822,
    "questionText": " Who was named Kumaran at his birth?",
    "answerText": " Poikayil Yohannan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87823,
    "questionText": " ‘Sanmarga Pradeepa Sabha’ at Kumbalam was patronised by?",
    "answerText": " Pandit Karuppan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87824,
    "questionText": " In which year Samastha Kerala Sahodara Sammelanam was held at Aluva?",
    "answerText": 1921
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87825,
    "questionText": " Which community was profoundly influenced by the ideals of Chattampi Swamikal?",
    "answerText": " Nair"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87826,
    "questionText": " Which organisation showed profound adherence to the principles enshrined by Chattampi Swamikal?",
    "answerText": " Nair Service Society"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87827,
    "questionText": " Who was deputed by Sree Narayana Guru in Sree Lanka to supervise the activities there?",
    "answerText": " Swami Satyavratha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87828,
    "questionText": " The social reformer whose mother’s name was Kuttiyamma?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87829,
    "questionText": " In which district Vakkom Abdul Khadir Moulaviwas born in 1873?",
    "answerText": " Thiruvananthapuram"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87830,
    "questionText": " The first book printed at Mannanam Press founded by Kuriakose Elias Chavara?",
    "answerText": " Gyanapiyusham"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87831,
    "questionText": " Who wrote ‘Anandavimanam’?",
    "answerText": " Brahmananda Sivayogi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87832,
    "questionText": " Whose mother was Veyilal?",
    "answerText": " Ayya Vaikuntar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87833,
    "questionText": " Whose birthday is observed as ‘Jeevakarunya Dinam’?",
    "answerText": " Chattampi Swamikal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87834,
    "questionText": " “Without differences of caste,Nor enmities of creed, Here it is, the model of an abode,where all live like brothers at heart” – at which place these words were inscribed by Narayana Guru on a plaque?",
    "answerText": " Aruvippuram"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87835,
    "questionText": " Who gave the name ‘Vagbhatananda’ to V.K.Gurukkal?",
    "answerText": " Sivayogi of Alathur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87836,
    "questionText": " At which place Chattampi Swamikal aquired self realization?",
    "answerText": " Vadaveeswaram"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87837,
    "questionText": " Whose childhood name was Ayyappan?",
    "answerText": " Chattampi Swamikal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87838,
    "questionText": " Who authored ‘Athmanuthaapam’?",
    "answerText": " Kuriakose Elias Chavara"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87839,
    "questionText": " Who authored ‘Nalagamangal’?",
    "answerText": " Kuriakose Elias Chavara"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87840,
    "questionText": " The place where the relics of Kuriakose Elias Chavara is kept?",
    "answerText": " Mannanam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87841,
    "questionText": " The social reformer whose native place is Swamithope?",
    "answerText": " Ayya Vaikuntar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87842,
    "questionText": " The social reformer whose father’s name is Vasudeva Sharma?",
    "answerText": " Chattampi Swamikal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87843,
    "questionText": " The social reformer whose ancestors were migrated from Malabar to Tamil Nadu during the invasion of Tipu Sultan?",
    "answerText": " Thycaud Ayya"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87844,
    "questionText": " Whois referred to as the “father of muslim renaissance in Kerala”?",
    "answerText": " Vakkom Moulavi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87845,
    "questionText": " From whom Mannath Padmanabhan received the Bharat Kesari honour?",
    "answerText": " Dr.Rajendra Prasad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87846,
    "questionText": " Name the publication started by Muhammad Abdur Rehman Sahib from Kozhikode in 1924?",
    "answerText": " Al Ameen"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87847,
    "questionText": " The date of birth of Chattampi Swamikal?",
    "answerText": " 25.09.1853"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87848,
    "questionText": " Who along with Vallabhasseri Govindan Vaidyar conceived the idea of Sivagiri Theerthadanam and presented it before Sree Narayana Guru?",
    "answerText": " T K Kittan Writer"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87849,
    "questionText": " Who wrote “Akilathirat’?",
    "answerText": " Ayya Vaikuntar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87850,
    "questionText": " Who wrote ‘Anandadarshanam’?",
    "answerText": " Brahmananda Sivayogi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87851,
    "questionText": " Who constructed a temple at Mangalam in 1852 for the avarnas?",
    "answerText": " Arattupuzha Velayudha Panicker"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87852,
    "questionText": " The first in south India to install mirror for worshipping?",
    "answerText": " Ayya Vaikuntar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87853,
    "questionText": " Who constituted a troup for practising and performing Kathakali under the aegis of Mangalam temple?",
    "answerText": " Arattupuzha Velayudha Panicker"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87854,
    "questionText": " Who authored ‘Anasthasiayude Rakthasakshyam’?",
    "answerText": " Kuriakose Elias Chavara"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87855,
    "questionText": " The social reformer who went to Goa to learn the rituals related to temples?",
    "answerText": " Arattupuzha Velayudha Panicker"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87856,
    "questionText": " Who wrote ‘Arulnool’?",
    "answerText": " Ayya Vaikuntar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87857,
    "questionText": " In which year the prefix ‘Mahakavi’ awarded to Kumaranasan by Madras University?",
    "answerText": 1922
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87858,
    "questionText": " The name ‘Sivagiri’ was given by?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87859,
    "questionText": " Who was the first to introduce the system called “A school along with every church”?",
    "answerText": " Kuriakose Elias Chavara"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87860,
    "questionText": " In which year Jagannatha Temple was founded at Thalassery by Sree Narayana Guru?",
    "answerText": 1908
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87861,
    "questionText": " The prompt explanation of which by Chattampi Swamikal was appreciated by Swami Vivekananda when the latter visited Kerala?",
    "answerText": " Chinmudra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87862,
    "questionText": " The foundation stone of which temple was laid by Annie Besant and was consecrated by Sree Narayana Guru?",
    "answerText": " Sreekanteswara Temple; Kozhikode"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87863,
    "questionText": " Which is the second temple where Sree Narayana Guru installed mirror in place of idol?",
    "answerText": " Ullala (Kottayam district)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87864,
    "questionText": " Which is regarded as the first work of Sree Narayana Guru?",
    "answerText": " Gajendramoksham Vanchippatt"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87865,
    "questionText": " Who became a member of Travancore Dewaswam Board when Mannath Padmanabhan became its president?",
    "answerText": " R.Shankar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87866,
    "questionText": " Aggrieved by the death of Sree Chattampi Swamikal, who wrote a condolence poem namely ‘Samadhi Sapthakam’?",
    "answerText": " Pandit Karuppan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87867,
    "questionText": " Who was the first secretary of Ananda Maha Sabha?",
    "answerText": " Rama Panicker"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87868,
    "questionText": " The social reformer who was known as ‘Daivadasan’?",
    "answerText": " Kuriakose Elias Chavara"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87869,
    "questionText": " Who mooted the idea that a school should be constructed with each church?",
    "answerText": " Kuriakose Elias Chavara"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87870,
    "questionText": " Who authored ‘Dhyanasallaapangal’?",
    "answerText": " Kuriakose Elias Chavara"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87871,
    "questionText": " Who wrote ‘Sthreevidyaposhini’?",
    "answerText": " Brahmananda Sivayogi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87872,
    "questionText": " Whose father was Ponnu Nadar?",
    "answerText": " Ayya Vaikuntar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87873,
    "questionText": " The social reformer who proscribed his followers from worshipping his picture?",
    "answerText": " Ayya Vaikuntar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87874,
    "questionText": " ‘Baalaakalesam’ was authored by?",
    "answerText": " Pandit Karuppan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87875,
    "questionText": " The elegy ‘Prarodanam’ mourns the death of Kumaranasan’s contemporary and friend ______?",
    "answerText": " A. R. Raja Raja Varma"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87876,
    "questionText": " Whose wife was Kamalammal?",
    "answerText": " Thycaud Ayya"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87877,
    "questionText": " Whose father is Muthukumaran?",
    "answerText": " Thycaud Ayya"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87878,
    "questionText": " In which year Ayya Vaikuntar passed away?",
    "answerText": 1851
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87879,
    "questionText": " The social reformer who proclaimed himself as an incarnation of Mahavishnu?",
    "answerText": " Ayya Vaikuntar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87880,
    "questionText": " In which year Kuriakose Elias Chavara was declared as a saint by Pope?",
    "answerText": 2014
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87881,
    "questionText": " Who demanded wages in accordance with labour?",
    "answerText": " Ayya Vaikuntar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87882,
    "questionText": " Who authored ‘Nalla Appante Chavarul’?",
    "answerText": " Kuriakose Elias Chavara"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87883,
    "questionText": " The greatest exponent of mishrabhojanam in the history of Kerala renaissance?",
    "answerText": " Sahhodaran Ayyappan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87884,
    "questionText": " Who started the publication ‘Vidyalayam’?",
    "answerText": " Moorkoth Kumaran"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87885,
    "questionText": " The famous leader whose birth place is Peralasseri in Kannur?",
    "answerText": " A.K.Gopalan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87886,
    "questionText": " Who wrote ‘Paropakari’?",
    "answerText": " Makthi Thangal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87887,
    "questionText": " In which year Ayyankali passed away?",
    "answerText": 1941
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87888,
    "questionText": " In which year Makthi Thangal was born?",
    "answerText": 1847
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87889,
    "questionText": " Who led the Perinad strike?",
    "answerText": " Ayyankali"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87890,
    "questionText": " Which organization is related to the slogan “To change the Nampoothiri into human”?",
    "answerText": " Yogakshema Sabha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87891,
    "questionText": " In which year the Goverment of Travancore issued orders to open the approach roads to temples to all avarnas?",
    "answerText": 1928
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87892,
    "questionText": " Name the social reformed who had contacts with Sree Narayana Guru and Brahmananda Sivayogi?",
    "answerText": " Vagbhatananda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87893,
    "questionText": " In which year Mannath Padmanabhan was elected to the Travancore Legislative Assembly?",
    "answerText": 1949
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87894,
    "questionText": " Name the leaders of renaissance of Kerala who kept a warm relationship throughout their life from the beginning of their friendship?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru and Chattampi Swamikal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87895,
    "questionText": " “The people who form the Ezhava samajam and Nair samajam are themselves proclaiming that they are nonBrahmins and are of backward class, thereby destroying their eminence and unity”-Who said this?",
    "answerText": " Brahmananda Sivayogi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87896,
    "questionText": " In order to provide opportunity of education for poor children, what was organized by V.T.Bhatathirippad?",
    "answerText": " Begging March (Yachana Yatra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87897,
    "questionText": " Whose ancestral home is’Koodilla Veedu’?",
    "answerText": " K.Ramakrishna Pillai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87898,
    "questionText": " Who was the first European disciple of Sree Narayana Guru?",
    "answerText": " Ernest Kirk"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87899,
    "questionText": " Thonnakkal in Thiruvananthapuram district is famous for the memorial of?",
    "answerText": " Kumaranasan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87900,
    "questionText": " Sahodaran Ayyappan memorial is at?",
    "answerText": " Idappally"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87901,
    "questionText": " Whom Dr.Palpu called ‘Chinna Swami’?",
    "answerText": " Kumaranasan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87902,
    "questionText": " The Keralite who wrote a book on ‘Karl Marx’ in 1912?",
    "answerText": " K Ramakrishna Pillai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87903,
    "questionText": " Swadeshabhimani K Ramakrishna Pillai was banished from Travancore for alleged charge of sedition, in the year?",
    "answerText": 1910
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87904,
    "questionText": " Veenapoovu, by Kumaranasan which marked the beginning of romanticism in Malayalam was published in ‘Mithavadhi’ in?",
    "answerText": 1907
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87905,
    "questionText": " The social reformer who wrote ‘Panchavadi’?",
    "answerText": " CV Kunjuraman"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87906,
    "questionText": " Who established ‘Atmavidhyasangham’?",
    "answerText": " Vagbhatananda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87907,
    "questionText": " Who started ‘Deshabhimani’ from Kollam in 1915, which published till 1930?",
    "answerText": " TK Madhavan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87908,
    "questionText": " Who was the first president of Nair service Society formed in 1914 as ‘Nair Bhrithyajana Sangham’?",
    "answerText": " K Kelappan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87909,
    "questionText": " In connection with which event, Gandhiji visited Kerala for the second time, in 1925?",
    "answerText": " Vaikom Satyagraha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87910,
    "questionText": " ‘Ente Jeevitha Katha’ is the autobiography of?",
    "answerText": " AK Gopalan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87911,
    "questionText": " ‘Ente Jeevithasmaranakal’ is the autobiography of?",
    "answerText": " Mannath Padmanabhan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87912,
    "questionText": " The year of commencement of Vaikom Satyagraha, the first Satyagraha in India against untouchablity?",
    "answerText": 1924
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87913,
    "questionText": " Who was instrumental in submitting a petition named ‘Ezhava Memorial’ in 1896 demanding appointments for Ezhavas in Govt services?",
    "answerText": " Dr.Palpu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87914,
    "questionText": " Who was the first signatory of Malayali Memorial?",
    "answerText": " K.P.Sankara Menon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87915,
    "questionText": " Whom Dr.Palpu called ‘Periya Swami’?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87916,
    "questionText": " The work of Kumaranasan based on Buddhist legend?",
    "answerText": " Chandalabhikshuki"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87917,
    "questionText": " Who served as the manager of Residency in Thiruvananthapuram?",
    "answerText": " Thycaud Ayya"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87918,
    "questionText": " Who authored ‘Adhyathmayuddham’?",
    "answerText": " Vagbhatananda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87919,
    "questionText": " The persolality who was known as ‘Bharat Kesari’?",
    "answerText": " Mannath Padmanabhan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87920,
    "questionText": " Onre ulakam, Onre matham, Onre Arasu, Onre neethi” who said this?",
    "answerText": " Ayya Vaikunatar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87921,
    "questionText": " In which session of the Indian National Congress T.K.Madhavan took initiative to introduce a resolution related to Vaikom Satyagraha?",
    "answerText": " Kakinada"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87922,
    "questionText": " Which newspaper started its publication on 18th March 1923?",
    "answerText": " Mathrubhumi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87923,
    "questionText": " The author of ‘Udhyanavirunnu’?",
    "answerText": " Pandit Karuppan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87924,
    "questionText": " Who established places of worship known as ‘Nizhal thangal’?",
    "answerText": " Ayya Vaikuntar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87925,
    "questionText": " The social reformer who was known as ‘Shanmukhadasa’?",
    "answerText": " Chattampi Swamikal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87926,
    "questionText": " Mannath Padmanabhan started his professional life as a?",
    "answerText": " Teacher"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87927,
    "questionText": " ‘Thuvayal Panthi’ was established by?",
    "answerText": " Ayya Vaikunatar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87928,
    "questionText": " Who wrote ‘Swaathanthrya gadha’?",
    "answerText": " Kumaranasan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87929,
    "questionText": " In a message to the Sree Narayana Dharma Paripalana Yogam in 1926 who declared, No community can make progress except through organization?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87930,
    "questionText": " The social reformer related to ‘Villuvandi Yatra’?",
    "answerText": " Ayyankali"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87931,
    "questionText": " Who established Narayana Gurukulam in 1923 in the Nilgiri Hills with the blessings of Nârâyana Guru?",
    "answerText": " Nataraja Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87932,
    "questionText": " Who called Sree Narayana Guru as ‘The Second Buddha’?",
    "answerText": " G. Sankara Kurup"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87933,
    "questionText": " Who ruled that Sivagiri pilgrims could wear yellow clothes - the colour of the garments Sri Buddha wore?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87934,
    "questionText": " The publication ‘Prabuddhakeralam’ was launched by?",
    "answerText": " Agamananda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87935,
    "questionText": " Whose home was ‘Sahithyakudeeram’?",
    "answerText": " Pandit Karuppan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87936,
    "questionText": " In which year Mannath Padmanabhan got the award ‘Bharat Kesari’?",
    "answerText": 1959
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87937,
    "questionText": " Who proclaimed It is years since I left castes and religions. Yet some people think that I belong to their caste. That is not correct. I do not belong to any particular caste or religion?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87938,
    "questionText": " A notable disciple of Sree Nârâyana Guru introduced Guru’s visions and ideals to the western world?",
    "answerText": " Nataraja Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87939,
    "questionText": " Which organization is related to the publication ‘Service’?",
    "answerText": " Nair Service Society"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87940,
    "questionText": " The real name of Agamananda?",
    "answerText": " Krishnan Nambiathiri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87941,
    "questionText": " Who was the Secretary of the committee for Abstention Movement in Travancore?",
    "answerText": " C.Kesavan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87942,
    "questionText": " In which year was the Villuvandi yatra of Ayyankali?",
    "answerText": 1893
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87943,
    "questionText": " ‘Unni Namboothiri’ is the publication of?",
    "answerText": " Yogakshema Sabha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87944,
    "questionText": " The first secretary of N.S.S?",
    "answerText": " Mannath Padmanabhan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87945,
    "questionText": " In which publication Dr.Palpu wrote with the pen name ‘Thiruvithamkotte Theeyan’?",
    "answerText": " Madras Standard"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87946,
    "questionText": " The first school of N.S.S. was started at?",
    "answerText": " Karukachal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87947,
    "questionText": " How many people signed the Ezhava Memorial?",
    "answerText": 13176
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87948,
    "questionText": " Who took initiative to establish Samastha Thiruvithamkur Pulayar Mahasabha?",
    "answerText": " T.T.Kesavan Sastri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87949,
    "questionText": " From which place the publication of Kerala Kaumudi was started in 1911?",
    "answerText": " Mayyanad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87950,
    "questionText": " At present where is the headquarters of Kerala Kaumudi?",
    "answerText": " Pettah in Thiruvananthapuram"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87951,
    "questionText": " The organisation in Kerala which was founded in the lines of Servants of India Society?",
    "answerText": " Nair Service Society"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87952,
    "questionText": " Who called Ayyankali ‘Pulayaraja’?",
    "answerText": " Mahathma Gandhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87953,
    "questionText": " Which was the mouth piece of Abstention Movement?",
    "answerText": " Kerala Kesari"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87954,
    "questionText": " At present the mouth piece of Sree Narayana Dharma Paripalana Yogam?",
    "answerText": " Yoganadam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87955,
    "questionText": " .Who suggested the name Nair Service Society?",
    "answerText": " K.Paramu Pillai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87956,
    "questionText": " All are of one Self-fraternity such being the dictum to avow, In such a light how can we take life And devoid of least pity go on to eat.who said?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87957,
    "questionText": " .Who led ‘Jeevasikha Jatha’ during the Liberation Struggle?",
    "answerText": " Mannath Padmanabhan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87958,
    "questionText": " Who called Ayyan Kali as Pulaya Raja?",
    "answerText": " Mahathma Gandhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87959,
    "questionText": " The social reformer who led Achipudava Samaram?",
    "answerText": " Arattupuzha Velayudha Panicker"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87960,
    "questionText": " In which year the Maharajah of Travancore exempted Nârâyana Guru from personal appearances in court, an honour recognizing the Guru as a distinguished living pTravancoreersonality?",
    "answerText": 1904
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87961,
    "questionText": " first planned and organized agitation for denied rights in the history of Kerala?",
    "answerText": " Vaikom Satyagraha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87962,
    "questionText": " Who wrote ‘Jathi Nirnayam’?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87963,
    "questionText": " Who was the president of the Guruvayur Satyagraha Committee?",
    "answerText": " Mannath Padmanabhan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87964,
    "questionText": " The Tamil Renaissance leader who was associated with the Vaikom Satyagraha of 1924-25?",
    "answerText": " E.V.Ramaswami Naicker"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87965,
    "questionText": " Who wrote ‘Nirvruthi Panchakam’?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87966,
    "questionText": " The leader of Paliyam Satyagraha who was killed in police action?",
    "answerText": " A.G.Velayudhan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87967,
    "questionText": " Who is related to the pen name ‘Thiruvithamkotte Theeyan’?",
    "answerText": " Dr.Palpu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87968,
    "questionText": " Who wrote ‘Brahmavidya Panchakam’ , a Sanskrit work?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87969,
    "questionText": " Who suggested the name ‘Nair Bhrithyajana Sangham’?",
    "answerText": " K.Kannan Menon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87970,
    "questionText": " Who was the chairman of the Antiuntouchability Committee formed at a conference held at Ernakulam in 1924?",
    "answerText": " K.Kelappa"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87971,
    "questionText": " ‘Jeevithasamaram’ is the autobiography of?",
    "answerText": " C.Kesavan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87972,
    "questionText": " The only leader in the world to bring down a Communist Government by public and democratic movement?",
    "answerText": " Mannath Padmanabhan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87973,
    "questionText": " Who was the king of Travancore when Vaikom Satyagraha was started?",
    "answerText": " Sri Mulam Tirunal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87974,
    "questionText": " Who came to the Satyagraha camp at Vaikom as an observer at Gandhij’s instence?",
    "answerText": " Vinoba Bhave"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87975,
    "questionText": " The king of Travancore who issued Temple Entry Proclamation?",
    "answerText": " Chithira Tirunal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87976,
    "questionText": " Sadhujana Paripalana Sangham founded by Ayyankali was modelled after?",
    "answerText": " SNDP Yogam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87977,
    "questionText": " In which year Cheramar Mahasabha was founded?",
    "answerText": 1921
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87978,
    "questionText": " The social reformer who married Thottakkad Madhavi Amma, the first woman member of Cochin Legislative Council?",
    "answerText": " Mannath Padmanabhan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87979,
    "questionText": " Who among the following actively participated in Vaikom Satyagraha but didn’t participated in Guruvayur Satyagraha as he had gone abroad to practise law?",
    "answerText": " K.P.Kesavamenon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87980,
    "questionText": " Name the prime minister who visited Kerala during the Liberation Struggle?",
    "answerText": " Jawaharlal Nehru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87981,
    "questionText": " What was the aim of Vaikom Satyagraha?",
    "answerText": " Open the approach road of the temple to avarnas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87982,
    "questionText": " The ruler of Travancore who stopped the Kudikkari or Devadasi system?",
    "answerText": " Sethulakshmi Bai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87983,
    "questionText": " The leader who exhorted the women of Kerala in 1931 to boycott temples as they had to remove upper cloths during festival seasons as a part of some rituals?",
    "answerText": " Mannath Padmanabhan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87984,
    "questionText": " “A smriti which is the people’s charter of spiritual emancipation” who hailed the Temple Entry Proclamation with these words?",
    "answerText": " Mahathma Gandhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87985,
    "questionText": " In which temple Sree Narayana Guru Installed a slab as idol with the words, “Sathyam’ (Truth), Dharmam (Ethics), Daya (Compassion), Sneham (love)”?",
    "answerText": " Murukkumpuzha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87986,
    "questionText": " The founder of Cheramar Mahasabha?",
    "answerText": " Pampadi John Joseph"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87987,
    "questionText": " After which notable incident Gandhiji visited Kerala for the last time?",
    "answerText": " Temple Entry Proclamation"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87988,
    "questionText": " The social activist who was killed in 1874 during a boat journey by a group of upperclass people?",
    "answerText": " Arattupuzha Velayudha Panicker"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87989,
    "questionText": " “One caste, One religion and One God for man of the same blood and form, there is no difference animals of the same caste alone procreate Viewed thus all humanity belong to one caste”- In which book of Sree Narayana Guru these words can be seen?",
    "answerText": " Jati Mimamsa"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87990,
    "questionText": " Who among the following built a Vihar for Budhhists and eventually became a Buddhist himself?",
    "answerText": " C.Krishnan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87991,
    "questionText": " The samadhi of Sree Narayana Guru is at?",
    "answerText": " Sivagiri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87992,
    "questionText": " “Pracheena Malayalam” is authored by?",
    "answerText": " Chattambi Swamikal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87993,
    "questionText": " The first statue of Sree Narayana Guru was unveiled at?",
    "answerText": " Thalassery"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87994,
    "questionText": " Who was the leader of opposition in Kerala Legislative Assembly during the Liberation Struggle?",
    "answerText": " P.T.Chacko"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87995,
    "questionText": " ‘Vavootuyogam’ was the predecessor of?",
    "answerText": " SNDP Yogam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87996,
    "questionText": " During the Liberation Struggle (1959), the ‘Jeevasikha Jatha’ led by Mannath Padmanabhan was started from?",
    "answerText": " Angamali"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87997,
    "questionText": " “If a temple perishes that much superstition will perish” who made this controversial statement?",
    "answerText": " C.Kesavan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87998,
    "questionText": " Whom Mannanth Padmanabhan once dubbed as his ‘political nephew’?",
    "answerText": " R.Sankar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 87999,
    "questionText": " Vaikom Satyagraha lasted for ____months?",
    "answerText": 20
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 88000,
    "questionText": " The immediate cause of the outbreak of the Liberation Struggle was the introduction of the?",
    "answerText": " Education Bill"
  }
]